<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">
    <title>Cogitate and Percolate</title>
    <link href="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog" />
    <updated>2025-08-04T16:32:23-04:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Heather Dodds</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog</id>

    <entry>
        <title>My Privacy Policy</title>
        <author>
            <name>Heather Dodds</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/my-privacy-policy.html"/>
        <id>https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/my-privacy-policy.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/740/sasun-bughdaryan-8admGA18lBs-unsplash.jpg" medium="image" />
            <category term="privacy"/>
            <category term="policy"/>

        <updated>2025-07-21T18:23:51-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/740/sasun-bughdaryan-8admGA18lBs-unsplash.jpg" alt="" />
                    With the results of the United States Presidential Election in November 2024, there was a tectonic shift in the thinking of individuals that do want to speak truth to power, but also do not want to be unwise in the act. My blog is primarily&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/740/sasun-bughdaryan-8admGA18lBs-unsplash.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <p>With the results of the United States Presidential Election in November 2024, there was a tectonic shift in the thinking of individuals that do want to speak truth to power, but also do not want to be unwise in the act. My blog is primarily about speaking the truth about XR for learning around and despite some very powerful companies and a few personal enemies.<br><br>I'm old enough that the lessons of World War II are not lost on me.  The time period between November 2024 and this blog going live in June/July 2025 has caused many to harken of 1920s Germany. Indeed, several new phrases have been circulating in my head.<br><br><a href="https://snyder.substack.com/p/twenty-lessons-read-by-john-lithgow" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer">Do not obey in advance</a> is one.<br><br>But another idea is <strong>to not give up my data</strong>, even if I'm utilizing my free speech rights as a US citizen. The idea that one would not be caught up in being arrested or worst <em>if</em> one is doing nothing wrong...is behind us. The monster eats and it eats anyone it can get.</p>
<figure class="d1fekHMv2WPYZzgPAV7b"><img  src="https://external-content.duckduckgo.com/iu/?u=https%3A%2F%2Fbecunningandfulloftricks.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F2014%2F09%2Fbe-cunning-and-full-of-tricks-header.jpg&amp;f=1&amp;nofb=1&amp;ipt=9ae1bc74285160c271a98a773ad982ccdd52c376fea91049e584a8ef12a627f8" alt="Be Cunning and Full of Tricks | Exploring Knowledge Management, Online Communities and Virtual ..." loading="eager" data-is-external-image="true"></figure>
<div class="quoteDetails">
<blockquote>
<div class="quoteText">“...Whenever they catch you, they will kill you. But first they must catch you, digger, listener, runner, prince with the swift warning. <strong>Be cunning and full of tricks</strong>...” <br>― <span class="authorOrTitle"> Richard Adams, Watership Down</span></div>
</blockquote>
</div>
<p><br>That idea lead me to the lovely <a href="https://www.optoutproject.net/" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer">Opt Out Project blog</a>.<br><br>Even though I had no direct reason for jumping ship from blogger/blogspot...how MUCH big tech is scraping personal accounts for data now just friggin scares me.  I left Twitter/X because of their new policy so take anything anyone posts as food for their AI.  I create and share my creations. I was like...uh, no, you are not free to take my stuff.  So I left, deleting everything in my wake.</p>
<figure class="post__image align-center"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/740//star-trek-spock-live-long-and-prosper.gif" alt="Gif of Spock saying Live long and prosper when by his face he means fuck off." width="498" height="211"></figure><br><br>Leaving blogger/blogspot is another in the steps I'm taking to get away from big tech.<br><br>So that means that you have arrived here. It took me 4 months to get this blog up and running.  To the best of my ability, here is what it does.<br><br>1. <strong>I don't care about number counting reads</strong>. Read counts stoke vanity. I've also never activated replies to my posts. If you want to respond, do so on your own blog, thankyouverymuch. 🧐 I try very hard to not count nor look at the numbers of anything I create.  It's not. about. the. numbers. 🚫🔢<br><br>2. This blog is hosted on Github Pages, which is at this time a Microsoft product. <strong>I encourage you to visit using a VPN</strong> because they are probably tracking IPs, but I do not receive the information. <strong>I do not have ANY analytics</strong> that I have activated on this blog.  <br><br>3. I'm using Publii and since I only post blog posts and nothing else (no stores, no forms, no mailing lists...I guess the kids call this static HTML now) <strong>I do not plan on adding ANY plugins</strong>. I'm using a basic theme available from Publii.  I'll let you know here and in the cookie banner if that changes in the future.<br><br>4. I'm going to attempt to set up the cookie banner to be meaningless for collecting anything and to strongly encourage you to Reject cookies. Let's hope I figure that out.</p>
<p>Oh and one more thing, <strong>I do not monetize anything here</strong>. Nothing.  By willingly turning my back on all forms of monetization, I'm never working for someone else that will show up as bias in my writing.<br><br>As Opt Out Project writes: <strong>No trackers. No fingerprints. No data collection.</strong><br><br>Let us all live long and prosper.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Part 6 Myth: Immersive learning is active learning</title>
        <author>
            <name>Heather Dodds</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/part-6-myth-immersive-learning-is-active-learning.html"/>
        <id>https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/part-6-myth-immersive-learning-is-active-learning.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/722/Immersive-Learning-is-not-necessarily-active-learning1.png" medium="image" />
            <category term="XR"/>
            <category term="VR"/>

        <updated>2025-01-21T14:13:00-05:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/722/Immersive-Learning-is-not-necessarily-active-learning1.png" alt="" />
                    The next myth is that learning in immersive experiences is active, kinesthetic, or like an internship, which is “the way most people learn best” (D’Agostino, 2022, para 17.) Spoiler: no it is not. Active learning was first associated with immersive experiences because learners could observe&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/722/Immersive-Learning-is-not-necessarily-active-learning1.png" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <p><span style="font-family: arial;">The next myth is that learning in immersive experiences is active, kinesthetic, or like an internship, which is “the way most people learn best” (D’Agostino, 2022, para 17.) Spoiler: no it is not.<br></span></p>
<p><span style="font-family: arial;"><br>Active learning was first associated with immersive experiences because learners could observe or engage with or, more properly described, engage within simulations (Dede, 2009). The term active simply meant that the learner was present at a simulated place and time; the original use of the active learning phrase with reference to immersive experiences did not imply that a learner could do anything other than observe. The emphasis was much more on the time and space travel afforded by XR.<br><br>This claim has been controversial (Khorasani et al., 2023), in part because of the differing degrees of activity that a learner can have - ranging from simply being inside an immersive environment and observing (e.g. historical re-enactment simulations) to taking actions that have non-trivial consequences (e.g. practicing a surgical technique).<br><br></span></p>
<h2 style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-family: arial;">Active learning is a phrase on the move</span></h2>
<p><span style="font-family: arial;"><br>Dede (2009) referred to <strong>actional immersion</strong> as situations where learner actions have “novel, intriguing consequences” that are “highly motivating and sharply focus attention.” (p. 66). The active learning claim moved from a focus on the <strong><i>learner’s actions</i></strong> and instead focused on the <strong><i>learner’s body ownership</i></strong> illusion. Further, the relationship between user bodies and virtual depictions (avatars) was reformulated and later called <strong>implicit learning</strong> (Slater, 2017, p. 29). <br><br>I want to pause here and really dissect the difference because in this area, there has definitely been vocabulary "drift".  Learner's actions focus on what the learner causes to happen.  Learner's body ownership focuses on parts of the body that the learner uses to cause actions.<br><br>For example, picture a chemistry lab simulation. </span></p>
<table class="tr-caption-container" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="0" align="center" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}">
<tbody>
<tr>
<td data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}"><a data-original-attrs="{&quot;data-original-href&quot;:&quot;https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEgOw3v80_MnxAeow0j0j9MHcvPonZTBILFwouDR4t3F-5fH80YCniKBUFf-ozH4SVmv3nkoxAh4aXsaAWlM7_j0sw631BT2jgE_WN90s4CLIJGGOfyy6c7-7albp4s_f8L8uRWTh8prRAmIFfPTduwKYcSw1V0ietzyUtG8PlRnZ2u930VISQeXMHTB-oo/s1216/chemistry%20pipette%20labster.jpg&quot;,&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}" href="https://draft.blogger.com/#"><img loading="lazy" src="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEgOw3v80_MnxAeow0j0j9MHcvPonZTBILFwouDR4t3F-5fH80YCniKBUFf-ozH4SVmv3nkoxAh4aXsaAWlM7_j0sw631BT2jgE_WN90s4CLIJGGOfyy6c7-7albp4s_f8L8uRWTh8prRAmIFfPTduwKYcSw1V0ietzyUtG8PlRnZ2u930VISQeXMHTB-oo/s320/chemistry%20pipette%20labster.jpg" width="320" height="229" border="0" data-original-height="870" data-original-width="1216" data-is-external-image="true"></a></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="tr-caption" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}">Image: Labster<br><br></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p><span style="font-family: arial; color: var(--text-primary-color); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">Focusing on the </span><strong style="font-family: arial; font-size: inherit;">learner's actions</strong><span style="font-family: arial; color: var(--text-primary-color); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);"> means that we could use a 2D display screen and mouse and have the learner click on the pipette, click on a liquid to suck up with the pipette, and then click on a vial within which to dispense the liquid.  Those could be right to left actions, but the learner is causing the actions to happen on the screen. They are using a mouse and moving their hand generally right to left.  No hand needs to be visible to do these actions. Activities could be "ghost like" in that they could be caused by no visual physical object whatsoever.  In reality, the computer mouse is doing the most physical 'work'.</span></p>
<div style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-family: arial;"><br>Focusing on the <strong>learner's body ownership</strong> however, would have the learner reaching out (they need to be able to reach) to the pipette, to grab it (they need to be able to firmly grasp), to possible depress the button on the top to create the needed suction, to move the pipette, see the liquid and subsequent vial, and depress the button to dispense the liquid. The movements could be all right to left. Key in this visual depiction, however, is A HAND with workable fingers that is somehow connection via experience to a learner's IRL hand.<br><br><br>In the former example, the learner causes the actions to occur but we are not focused on their body parts doing the action. In the latter example, we are very interested in the body parts doing work that is replicate (in this case) to the real world work of operating a pipette. In the former, we could have confidence that a learner is exposed to the cause and effect of pipette work; it sucks up a reliable amount of liquid and can squirt it back out. In the latter, we could have confidence that a learner is exposed to how pipettes physically work (button press down equal prime for suck, release equals suck, button press down again equals squirt).  <br><br>See that the focus is different?<br><br>My point is that the FOCUS of what was coming to be called <strong><i>active learning</i></strong> with reference to XR was changing already between 2009 and 2017.</span></div>
<p><span style="font-family: arial;"><br>Drawing from the educational history of the Montessori method and considering the interfaces available within immersive experiences, implicit bodily learning (from 2017) transformed to <strong>embodied learning</strong> (by 2018). Indeed, Johnson-Glenberg initially postulated that “doing actual physical gestures in a virtual environment should have positive, and lasting, effects on learning in the real world” (2018, p. 1). <i>Movement became synonymous with active learning</i>. “Active, motor-driven concepts may stimulate distributed semantic networks (meaning), as well as the associated motor cortices which would have been used to learn long ago, in childhood” (Johson Glenberg, 2018 p. 3). [Hat tip, by the way to all research into the mind-body connection within learning. This post throws no shade on the phenomena.] With specific, other than meaningful, actions now excluded, some researchers appeared to support the claim that all movement somehow begets learning. (That sentence is confusing, I wrote it and even I'm wondering what I meant. It's this: Inside a XR-for-learning experience, a learner might be instructed to do something. Pick this up, move it there.  Because that learning is specific to the learning event, I'm setting it aside. It's not part of this argument.  What I am referring to are the learner-instigated but non-instructed movements. Let's say, a learner joins XR and wanders to the left for 2 minutes before a lesson begins. Or let's say instead of looking to the "front" at the end of the experience, the learner is looking to the "back". These random but learner-instigated actions are...wait for it...somehow the secret sauce of learning in XR.  I kid you not. I really try to pin down the meaning from educators that belief this myth and THIS is what they come up with; because you can move in XR, you are learning (more) in XR.<br></span></p>
<p><a data-original-attrs="{&quot;data-original-href&quot;:&quot;https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEgzW4W730GqMoCcrWBtvAmRcJ1umbwzGPiQECNx9riNNOGBWU0qcfZDHI_PMT_PO7tzUPkEtzc6Uf-4GHzKjDjKqLbUHtdx5wYYN8B3I9gzv-Y-96N5dopOgKvjF3aYTfNGNUGfHKDSuws2Ju8jYkB9Ctjyn1e8NSAA6KkR6c4p7sF3vion862wjqZOGHc/s735/active%20learning.png&quot;}" href="https://draft.blogger.com/#"><img loading="lazy" src="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEgzW4W730GqMoCcrWBtvAmRcJ1umbwzGPiQECNx9riNNOGBWU0qcfZDHI_PMT_PO7tzUPkEtzc6Uf-4GHzKjDjKqLbUHtdx5wYYN8B3I9gzv-Y-96N5dopOgKvjF3aYTfNGNUGfHKDSuws2Ju8jYkB9Ctjyn1e8NSAA6KkR6c4p7sF3vion862wjqZOGHc/s320/active%20learning.png" border="0" data-is-external-image="true"></a></p>
<p><span style="font-family: arial;">The supporting hypothesis then became that immersive experiences are an inherently active learning method precisely because the learner can move. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-family: arial;"> I'm going to repeat that for emphasis:<br><br><br></span></p>
<blockquote>
<p><span style="font-family: arial;">The supporting hypothesis then became that immersive experiences <i><strong>are</strong></i> an inherently active learning method precisely because the learner <i><strong>can</strong></i> move. </span></p>
</blockquote>
<table class="tr-caption-container" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="0" align="center">
<tbody>
<tr>
<td style="text-align: center;"><a href="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEiXOqCDuyToT7oB9H-Hib1yb58sqhxgRmCYWEd_Y5RXtbCLPT6BA6xTWjVu3U-ftxm4xrJTpNtIPCNd9K6f2jzOETkCJBbzC4f_4soNnNMfgTu0mT1kaCitbxWgaMwJElxt-uc0LEql-a2hal3HC7DhBYsOXLcshOMcIsH8aFDsRZWb3Tvkdq-1LktbReA/s2181/Page_45_illustration_in_fairy_tales_of_Andersen_(Stratton).png" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"><img loading="lazy" src="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/722/Page_45_illustration_in_fairy_tales_of_Andersen_(Stratton).png" width="472" height="640" border="0" sizes="(max-width: 1920px) 100vw, 1920px" srcset="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/722/responsive/Page_45_illustration_in_fairy_tales_of_Andersen_(Stratton)-xs.png 640w ,https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/722/responsive/Page_45_illustration_in_fairy_tales_of_Andersen_(Stratton)-sm.png 768w ,https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/722/responsive/Page_45_illustration_in_fairy_tales_of_Andersen_(Stratton)-md.png 1024w ,https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/722/responsive/Page_45_illustration_in_fairy_tales_of_Andersen_(Stratton)-lg.png 1366w ,https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/722/responsive/Page_45_illustration_in_fairy_tales_of_Andersen_(Stratton)-xl.png 1600w ,https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/722/responsive/Page_45_illustration_in_fairy_tales_of_Andersen_(Stratton)-2xl.png 1920w"></a></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="tr-caption" style="text-align: center;"><span style="font-family: arial;">The Emperor's New Clothes. Image by Helen Stratton, Public domain, via Wikimedia Commons</span></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p><span style="font-family: arial;">Did you catch that? Aren't the emperor's new clothes splendid?</span></p>
<p><span style="font-family: arial;">By incorporating the word “active” educators are reminded of the belief that active learning is better than passive learning (Slater, 2017). Ooo! Shade thrown there, for sure, because no teacher wants to be accused of being a passive educator.<br><br></span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-family: arial;">[BTW, there is reams of garbage research out there for anyone looking for a topic. Go ahead and dig into active versus passive in educational psychology papers. It's almost as big of a research garbage dump as XR; teachers radically redefine and appeal to this topic. My point is that the appeal to "active learning" when coupled with XR provides scant evidence of such. To this day, I RARELY see active learning in XR.]</span></p>
<p><span style="font-family: arial;"><br>Let's bear down now. To be specific, the 'active learning' coupling with 'XR' claim is not about being fidgety, randomly moving about, or purely reacting as a user would in a game. It is movement, usually performed by the learner via an avatar or minimally via hand controllers where the learner is autonomously and purposely manipulating content.  This is known as embodiment or embodied learning (Johnson-Glenberg, 2018; Markowitz et al., 2018) although definitions of embodiment vary. The definitions vary including how much a learner is embodied. It should also be noted that the term<i> embodiment</i> is often used interchangeably with ‘embodied learning’, which is a theory that the meaningful gestures in and with the environment aid a learner’s cognitive processes (that's the no shade thing I referred to earlier). But even 'embodiment' and 'embodied learning' are slightly different things. Whew! Keeping up?<br></span></p>
<h2 style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-family: arial;">The Emperor's clothes <em>should be</em> splendid </span></h2>
<p><span style="font-family: arial;"><br>In 2018, Johnson-Glenberg claimed that presence and embodiment were “profound affordances” of immersive environments and this embodiment affordance should facilitate learner control, also known as agency (p. 1). One further hat tip to Mina: she did actually use a somewhat scientific body action in her research --I believe it was catching butterflies with a butterfly net-- something that biologists WOULD do with their bodies. So it's a real world action.  I point this out because some XR actions are nonsensical. I'm looking at you people who change vocabulary words to bouncing balls or something.</span></p>
<h2 style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-family: arial;">But aren't</span></h2>
<p><span style="font-family: arial;"><br>A follow-up paper by Mina, however, found that while embodiment does have a connection to learning, it does not exclusively cause learning, or perhaps better said,<strong> it doesn't interact with learning</strong>. Referring to high or low embodied VR and the connection to learning, “platform is not destiny” (Johnson‐Glenberg et al., 2021, p. 20). So in lay talk that means it had no effect.</span></p>
<table class="tr-caption-container" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="0" align="center">
<tbody>
<tr>
<td style="text-align: center;"><a href="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEi5UVzAzIiuxEwvXQ77vWF4KwauvncG6m2Jmq3bMdMj3BEDK-xRAdb-06mYNRts1K8teAQmveoiju86w0IfmZbW1GQmwsJKCZo8mcc9w9LgMjBFtCzqJr2SopswbIF6frg5UmCMhcZi8HIcrBgIci9GTMFVJiiiDx1AUow1j0DX9XUmZ7vNi0RdmGn3Xuc/s769/Screen_Shot_2021-05-17_at_12.04_.50_PM_.png" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"><img loading="lazy" src="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/722/Screen_Shot_2021-05-17_at_12.04_.50_PM_.png" width="320" height="262" border="0" sizes="(max-width: 1920px) 100vw, 1920px" srcset="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/722/responsive/Screen_Shot_2021-05-17_at_12.04_.50_PM_-xs.png 640w ,https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/722/responsive/Screen_Shot_2021-05-17_at_12.04_.50_PM_-sm.png 768w ,https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/722/responsive/Screen_Shot_2021-05-17_at_12.04_.50_PM_-md.png 1024w ,https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/722/responsive/Screen_Shot_2021-05-17_at_12.04_.50_PM_-lg.png 1366w ,https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/722/responsive/Screen_Shot_2021-05-17_at_12.04_.50_PM_-xl.png 1600w ,https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/722/responsive/Screen_Shot_2021-05-17_at_12.04_.50_PM_-2xl.png 1920w"></a></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="tr-caption" style="text-align: center;"><span style="font-family: arial;">A capture that fell flat with the audience: VR had no effect on learning, even when embodied.</span></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p><span style="background-color: transparent; color: black; font-size: 11pt; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: 400; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline;"><br> </span><br><span style="font-family: arial;">This confounding (confusing/muddling up/drift of vocabulary) of movement in immersive experiences with active learning forms the myth. Because active learning is considered better than passive learning, claims are made that immersive experiences must cause more learning due to the body-movement connection. The research, however, does not support that claim.<br><br>The active learning myth appears to be referred to more often in academic literature than evidence to the contrary. It is true that immersive experiences can allow for more movement-based learning experiences than other forms of media, but it is not definitive that immersive experiences cause learning simply because they can contain learner movement or agency.</span></p>
<blockquote>
<p><span style="font-family: arial;"><br><br>Just because you <i>can</i> move in XR, doesn't mean you <i>do</i> learn. Full stop.</span></p>
</blockquote>
<p><span style="font-family: arial;"><br></span>Part 7 will be our last myth for this series: Immersive learning causes empathy.</p>
<hr>
<h2 style="text-align: left;">References</h2>
<p><br>D’Agustino, S. (2022, August 3). College in the metaverse is here. Is higher ed ready? Inside Higher Ed. <a href="https://www.insidehighered.com/news/2022/08/03/college-metaverse-here-higher-ed-ready">https://www.insidehighered.com/news/2022/08/03/college-metaverse-here-higher-ed-ready</a><br><br>Dede, C. (2009). Immersive interfaces for engagement and learning. Science, 323(5910), 66–69. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1126/science.1167311">https://doi.org/10.1126/science.1167311</a><br><br>Johnson-Glenberg, M. C. (2018). Immersive VR and education: Embodied design principles that include gesture and hand controls. Frontiers in Robotics and AI, 81.<br><br>Johnson‐Glenberg, M. C., Bartolomea, H., &amp; Kalina, E. (2021). Platform is not destiny: Embodied learning effects comparing 2D desktop to 3D virtual reality STEM experiences. Journal of Computer Assisted Learning, 37(5), 1263-1284.<br><br>Khorasani, S., Syiem, B. V., Nawaz, S., Knibbe, J., &amp; Velloso, E. (2023). Hands-on or hands-off: Deciphering the impact of interactivity on embodied learning in VR. Computers &amp; Education: X Reality, 3, 100037.<br><br>Markowitz, D. M., Laha, R., Perone, B. P., Pea, R. D., &amp; Bailenson, J. N. (2018). Immersive virtual reality field trips facilitate learning about climate change. Frontiers in Psychology, 9, 2364. <br><br>Slater, M. (2017). Implicit learning through embodiment in immersive virtual reality. Virtual, augmented, and mixed realities in education, 19-33.</p>
<hr>
<p>Did you miss the other parts of this series? Here they are!</p>
<p><strong><a href="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/part-1-from-myths-to-principles-navigating-instructional-design-in-immersive-environments.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Part 1: From Myths To Principles: Navigating Instructional Design in Immersive Environments</a></strong></p>
<p><strong><a href="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/part-2-the-immersive-environment-delusion.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Part 2: The Immersive Environment Delusion</a></strong></p>
<p><strong><a href="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/part-3-the-case-against-virtual-campuses.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Part 3: The Case Against Virtual Campuses</a></strong></p>
<p><strong><a href="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/part-4-myth-learners-learn-faster.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Part 4: Myth: Learners Learn Faster</a></strong></p>
<p><strong><a href="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/part-5-myth-learners-learn-more.html">Part 5: Myth: Learners Learn More<br><br></a><a href="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/part-6-myth-immersive-learning-is-active-learning.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Part 6: Myth: Immersive learning is active learning</a></strong></p>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Part 5: Myth: Learners Learn More</title>
        <author>
            <name>Heather Dodds</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/part-5-myth-learners-learn-more.html"/>
        <id>https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/part-5-myth-learners-learn-more.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/723/The_foundation_of_all_learning_or_childs_first_book_by_which_a_child_will_learn_more_in_one_month_than_by_many_others_in_twelve_Fleuron_T118611-23.png" medium="image" />
            <category term="XR"/>

        <updated>2025-01-13T14:53:00-05:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/723/The_foundation_of_all_learning_or_childs_first_book_by_which_a_child_will_learn_more_in_one_month_than_by_many_others_in_twelve_Fleuron_T118611-23.png" alt="Wood cut image in black and white of a country scene with a large castle, a large fortress, and a shining sun." />
                    This myth shrouds itself within a cloak of research. Citations will state that learning in immersive experiences is somehow greater when pitted against an implied traditional learning approach. The claim could appear as retention, but it is related to how well the learning was accomplished when&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/723/The_foundation_of_all_learning_or_childs_first_book_by_which_a_child_will_learn_more_in_one_month_than_by_many_others_in_twelve_Fleuron_T118611-23.png" class="type:primaryImage" alt="Wood cut image in black and white of a country scene with a large castle, a large fortress, and a shining sun." /></p>
                <p> </p>
<h1>Myth: Learners learn more in immersive experiences</h1>
<p> </p>
<p>This <span style="font-family: helvetica;" data-keep-original-tag="false" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}">myth shrouds itself within a cloak of research. Citations will state that learning in immersive experiences is somehow greater when pitted against an <i>implied</i> traditional learning approach. The claim could appear as retention, but it is related to how well the learning was accomplished when measured up against learning objectives or a final goal.</span></p>
<p dir="ltr" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}"><span style="font-family: helvetica;" data-keep-original-tag="false" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}">When referring to the PricewaterhouseCooper (PwC) report results mentioned earlier in this article series, Scott Likens claimed, “We found the realism and performance feedback in virtual reality simulations helped people learn faster and retain more information around soft skills,” (Zielinski, 2021, para. 9). He claimed they <strong>retained more information</strong>. This specific claim has been <i>repeated</i> in academic literature, which stated, “Studies have found that students who use XR training are more engaged with the content, display more confidence with the material, and retain more information than students who use traditional training methods.” (Rode, 2024, para 2.)</span></p>
<p dir="ltr" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}"><span style="font-family: helvetica;" data-keep-original-tag="false" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}">A close examination of the PwC report, however, reveals that the claim was unsupported within the report’s own data. When comparing information retention in VR versus an e-learning course, the authors “quickly discovered retention scores were inconclusive, as the delta between pre-and post-assessments in each modality was not significant” (Eckert &amp; Mower, 2020, p. 44). Thus, there was no statistical difference between VR-based, e-learning, and traditional classroom learning.</span></p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEg6mXzovILnq5PhLfvka80xRhyBlaJcxnl4tWCfaWD31lIQY8YOolRhy-ZqhLqSo-gPu50AyhyphenhyphenLCLIdkov3cMNbOwRY8hBt8RZQzHJ5ROSuWD2k5vdyaHNwX1Xw3HxkRssn4UdIaAPTWx-ijbJIisNPR2YZXoFBsmmHhlI-XJIxTrFhwjGjNyteEJi05_U/w640-h438/PwC%20page%2044%20no%20statistical%20difference%20in%20learning.png" width="640" height="438" border="0" data-original-height="603" data-original-width="882" data-is-external-image="true"><figcaption><span style="font-family: helvetica;" data-keep-original-tag="false" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}">Claiming something happened but your instrument didn't pick it up <br>is the knomes-did-it territory of cause-and-effect, dudes. <br>Watch out.</span></figcaption></figure>
<p>The r<span style="font-family: helvetica;" data-keep-original-tag="false" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}">eport therefore does not provide statistical evidence of more or greater learning within VR, yet it has been cited in academic publications (O'Dwyer, 2021, Etienne et al., 2022,  Jelki et al., 2022; Bäckelin, 2023; Etienne et al., 2023; Lønne et al,. 2023) and touted in media outlets (Murad, 2023; Schwantes, 2020). For the dubious claims, the report has been debunked as untrustworthy (Neelen &amp; Kirschner, 2020). </span></p>
<p dir="ltr" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}"><span style="font-family: helvetica;" data-keep-original-tag="false" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}">There are similar claims about greater learning retained from immersive experiences. Advocates for digital twin campus environments claimed that they “create greater retention of the information that is learned” (D’Agustino, 2022, para. 5) and “students' grades go up” (Victory XR, 2024, Who We Are).</span></p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEiVtRaIf6D0-DZ35tyes7u91J2H6vSQi-mVSvSsEQm4TIdBVlT4Ay6MKtGOSqtbCvU2wvgeebntuMK9WkM-VZfIfUTkAQcvRBAUJX6Sq7jYYLdpdejJWUmQ6wu26td6Z7ZcVdMuehrUW6ptF35WMpRuSq5geuBivugb5l2DarlGRR8zjkWMCi6Q8swX-MM/s320/victory%20XR%20students%20grades%20go%20up_highlight.png" width="215" height="320" border="0" data-original-height="1022" data-original-width="688" data-is-external-image="true"><figcaption><span style="font-family: helvetica;" data-keep-original-tag="false" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}">While this is just one tiny sentence, keep in mind how much money VictoryXR makes from these claims.</span></figcaption></figure>
<p><span style="font-family: helvetica;" data-keep-original-tag="false" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}">In another example, the CEO of the Miami Children’s Health System touted that learners had 80% retention after one year after using VR, but traditional learners had 20% retention. A close look at the supporting documentation shows that the CEO actually said that the difference between VR learners and traditional learners can be the 80% to 20% difference. </span></p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEgdG1bKxgXTEBshJAUAG2Ti0xq9Hq4YEc67wxltVN-3_OEMy8sV_QgvbZ7vHMRw35T_8ZclS3YcPovSGtBCrWFoPu3t2fJqo0U5Ux40pSNXvMRyS7pRLpd9elapHJudFrcrYp8qjzP9GIquWHi5y7HQtvm8IqFzzOfjRum-PbEFq-QQDPYvFgNhvimgJ5c/s320/Axon%20Park%206%20400%20percent%20increase%20in%20long%20term%20retention.png" width="320" height="125" border="0" data-original-height="374" data-original-width="960" data-is-external-image="true"><figcaption></figcaption></figure>
<p dir="ltr" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}"><span style="font-family: helvetica;" data-keep-original-tag="false" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}">However, the CEO’s statement did not refer to any published results; it was opinion. The CEO explained their claim by saying that, “The level of understanding through VR is great because humans are primarily visual, and VR is a visual format” (Gaudiosi, 2021, para. 4). Cue learning styles!</span></p>
<p dir="ltr" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}"><a data-original-attrs="{&quot;data-original-href&quot;:&quot;https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEjNF4iZM6Y5D0_EFQzh-WYAJBbie_ljTm-GvkG3xhIKDuX-bbr8PqIUm6S2Ov04xanKwMe5qjTOzmtMspH-9jcvNQPpmQPCW8XwMwvpsDjcQDmOybVx8pLYRTLHvcLSsmiIZK2lhwnk-oQIsO4dLE2jtfORLfEJBsh7UxJY1xjiX0HzMofac-hkNB4hw20/s536/hands%20on%20learning.jpg&quot;,&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}" href="https://draft.blogger.com/#"><img loading="lazy" src="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEjNF4iZM6Y5D0_EFQzh-WYAJBbie_ljTm-GvkG3xhIKDuX-bbr8PqIUm6S2Ov04xanKwMe5qjTOzmtMspH-9jcvNQPpmQPCW8XwMwvpsDjcQDmOybVx8pLYRTLHvcLSsmiIZK2lhwnk-oQIsO4dLE2jtfORLfEJBsh7UxJY1xjiX0HzMofac-hkNB4hw20/s320/hands%20on%20learning.jpg" width="299" height="320" border="0" data-original-height="536" data-original-width="500" data-is-external-image="true"></a></p>
<p dir="ltr" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}"><span style="font-family: helvetica;" data-keep-original-tag="false" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}">Nonetheless, the quote of 80% retention has made its way into academic research (Iacono &amp; Vercelli, 2019; Mathew &amp; Pillai, 2020; Ternès, 2018). Some claims are extreme. One keynote speaker, Alvin Graylin, speaking as a leader at HTC (a VR headset maker) declared that as a result of VR use in the classroom, “Every single child has the potential to be a genius” (Educators in VR, 2020, 23:33).</span></p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEhJh2bl72HqXarw8R6BuFX4Qou_H5-6PtDner1tygfzvffYmYE1SJBI2YNmRVEIb9jfm8OExtcqHdhTZAKYdvLTtdDcJe6cN5ROjm5uuL2TTA2J-Tkg8zm8sgxZWHuLRcwCVbLQdjrELV0H9Ofu5BHrCLnc70-kYOLIGtFai14JMOe3NvcpnHKV5VNGzlU/w400-h330/every%20child%20can%20be%20a%20genius%20alvin%20graylin.png" width="400" height="330" border="0" data-original-height="754" data-original-width="915" data-is-external-image="true"><figcaption><span style="font-family: helvetica;" data-keep-original-tag="false" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}">"Every single child has the potential to be a genius." <br>You just need to buy a (HTC) headset.</span></figcaption></figure>
<p dir="ltr" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}"><span style="font-family: helvetica;" data-keep-original-tag="false" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}">Justification for the greater learning or retention claims seems to be conjecture. Claims refer to how real an immersive experience feels to a learner. Returning to the PwC report, Likens credited “the realism and performance feedback…helped people..retain more information.” (Zielinski, 2021, para. 9). But <strong>long term studies measuring retention are hard to find</strong> within the body of academic literature. Some studies measure retention three weeks after the immersive experiences. Given that many of the examples of immersive experiences relate to hands-on disciplines like nursing or construction, things learned in immersive experiences would be needed on the job more than three weeks after the training.</span></p>
<p dir="ltr" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}"><span style="font-family: helvetica;" data-keep-original-tag="false" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}">Hamilton et al. (2020) stated that finding “learning outcomes, intervention characteristics, and assessment measures associated with immersive virtual reality has been sparse” (p. 1). Beck, Morgado, and O’Shea (2023) pointed out that details of methods are missing so that outcomes become questionable, “Very few literature reviews focus on the educational practices and strategies used in immersive learning environments. Thus, the problem is that we are evaluating outcomes without a comparable way to describe the educational approaches that led to those outcomes” (p. 2). Lawson et al. (2024) completed a systematic review of immersive experiences and found that research studies rarely isolate instructional methods and conditions when describing research studies and thus impact real world classroom decisions.</span></p>
<p dir="ltr" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}"><span style="font-family: helvetica;" data-keep-original-tag="false" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}">Meta analyses are starting to illuminate this area. Akgün and Atıcı (2022) observed that there was only a moderate effect on learner achievement after surveying 31 studies. Kaplan, Cruit, Endsley, Beers, Sawyer and Hancock found that “XR does not express a different outcome than training in a non-simulated, control environment. It is equally effective at enhancing performance” (2020, p. 1) Some researchers are starting to incorporate machine learning and artificial intelligence into this challenge in order to determine what the published records states about immersive experiences. Markowitz et al. (2024) recently surveyed 196,734 paper abstracts with this method.</span></p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEiAMI6xY9uqy20HvUKtKwFmBQff_uhxxzohtbHQcYcxaKsnhDl8MQS-TeQLUzoK36UdTJO8mhj5Ev6Dj0TtSOAeGm4E69ZUw6Izk9ykpoR-6fE0zenMAo0ME2tAU7Ucl0h1GGDuvemAtYPad6zOoOBWbEtUwVFgczxmnNcP3r2_thgMF4qdJjOGz99uF48/w640-h340/Kaplan%20no%20difference%20graph.png" width="640" height="340" border="0" data-original-height="399" data-original-width="753" data-is-external-image="true"><figcaption><span style="font-family: helvetica;" data-keep-original-tag="false" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}">Basically this graph says that because the numbers are so small and so close to zero, there is no discernible effect of VR on learning, regardless of immersion (Kaplan et al., 2020).</span></figcaption></figure>
<h2 data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}">Myth: Learners learn more in immersive experiences</h2>
<p data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}">I find this myth is misleading. If immersive learning is compared to other forms of learning, all other variables must be held the same in order for the results to be considered valid. More on the faults of comparative media studies will be covered in another section of this series.</p>
<hr>
<h1 data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}"><span style="font-size: medium;" data-keep-original-tag="false" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}"><span style="font-family: helvetica;" data-keep-original-tag="false" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}">References</span></span></h1>
<p data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}"><span style="font-size: medium;" data-keep-original-tag="false" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}"><span style="font-family: helvetica;" data-keep-original-tag="false" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}">Akgün, M., &amp; Atıcı, B. (2022). The effects of immersive virtual reality environments on students' academic achievement: A meta-analytical and meta-thematic study. Participatory Educational Research, 9(3), 111-131.</span></span></p>
<p data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}"><span style="font-size: medium;" data-keep-original-tag="false" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}"><span style="font-family: helvetica;" data-keep-original-tag="false" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}">Bäckelin, J. (2023, August). Afraid or prepared-using dialogue training to practice crisis leadership in municipalities. In International Symposium on Digital Transformation.</span></span></p>
<p data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}"><span style="font-size: medium;" data-keep-original-tag="false" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}"><span style="font-family: helvetica;" data-keep-original-tag="false" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}">Beck, D., Morgado, L., &amp; O'Shea, P. (2023). Educational practices and strategies with immersive learning environments: Mapping of reviews for using the metaverse. IEEE Transactions on Learning Technologies, 17, 319-341. </span></span></p>
<p data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}"><span data-keep-original-tag="false" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}"><span style="font-size: medium;" data-keep-original-tag="false" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}"><span style="font-family: helvetica;" data-keep-original-tag="false" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}">D’Agustino, S. (2022, August 3). College in the metaverse is here. Is higher ed ready? Inside Higher Ed. <a data-original-attrs="{&quot;data-original-href&quot;:&quot;https://www.insidehighered.com/news/2022/08/03/college-metaverse-here-higher-ed-ready&quot;}" href="https://draft.blogger.com/#" rel="nofollow">https://www.insidehighered.com/news/2022/08/03/college-metaverse-here-higher-ed-ready</a>  <br></span></span></span></p>
<p data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}"><span style="font-size: medium;" data-keep-original-tag="false" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}"><span style="font-family: helvetica;" data-keep-original-tag="false" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}">Eckert, D., &amp; Mower, A. (2020). The effectiveness of virtual reality soft skills training in the enterprise: a study. PwC Public Report. <a data-original-attrs="{&quot;data-original-href&quot;:&quot;https://www.pwc.com/us/en/services/consulting/technology/emerging-technology/assets/pwc-understanding-the-effectiveness-of-soft-skills-training-in-the-enterprise-a-study.pdf&quot;,&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;target&quot;:&quot;_blank&quot;}" href="https://draft.blogger.com/#" rel="nofollow">https://www.pwc.com/us/en/services/consulting/technology/emerging-technology/assets/pwc-understanding-the-effectiveness-of-soft-skills-training-in-the-enterprise-a-study.pdf</a> </span></span></p>
<p data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}"><span style="font-size: medium;" data-keep-original-tag="false" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}"><span style="font-family: helvetica;" data-keep-original-tag="false" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}">Educators in VR. (2020, February 20). Alvin Wang Graylin – Keynote (Alvin Wang Graylin) [Video]. YouTube. <a data-original-attrs="{&quot;data-original-href&quot;:&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-xT0sCUkJ-U&quot;,&quot;target&quot;:&quot;_blank&quot;}" href="https://draft.blogger.com/#" rel="nofollow">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-xT0sCUkJ-U</a> </span></span></p>
<p data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}"><span style="font-size: medium;" data-keep-original-tag="false" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}"><span style="font-family: helvetica;" data-keep-original-tag="false" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}">Etienne, E., Leclercq, A. L., Remacle, A., &amp; Schyns, M. (2022). Validation of a virtual framework for public speaking training. [Paper presentation]. 7th International XR Conference, Lisbon, Portugal. <a data-original-attrs="{&quot;data-original-href&quot;:&quot;https://orbi.uliege.be/bitstream/2268/290274/1/Revised%20AR_VR%20abstractdec2021-22.pdf&quot;,&quot;target&quot;:&quot;_blank&quot;}" href="https://draft.blogger.com/#" rel="nofollow">https://orbi.uliege.be/bitstream/2268/290274/1/Revised%20AR_VR%20abstractdec2021-22.pdf</a></span></span></p>
<p data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}"><span style="font-size: medium;" data-keep-original-tag="false" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}"><span style="font-family: helvetica;" data-keep-original-tag="false" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}">Etienne, E., Leclercq, A., Remacle, A., Dessart, L., &amp; Schyns, M. (2023). Perception of avatars nonverbal behaviors in virtual reality. Psychology and Marketing, 40(11), 2464–2481. <a data-original-attrs="{&quot;data-original-href&quot;:&quot;https://doi.org/10.1002/mar.21871&quot;,&quot;target&quot;:&quot;_blank&quot;}" href="https://draft.blogger.com/#" rel="nofollow">https://doi.org/10.1002/mar.21871</a>  <br></span></span></p>
<p data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}"><span style="font-size: medium;" data-keep-original-tag="false" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}"><span style="font-family: helvetica;" data-keep-original-tag="false" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}">Gaudiosi J.  (2015, August 17). Here's why hospitals are using virtual reality to train staff. Fortune. <a data-original-attrs="{&quot;data-original-href&quot;:&quot;https://fortune.com/2015/08/17/virtual-reality-hospitals/&quot;,&quot;target&quot;:&quot;_blank&quot;}" href="https://draft.blogger.com/#" rel="nofollow">https://fortune.com/2015/08/17/virtual-reality-hospitals/</a></span></span></p>
<p data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}"><span style="font-size: medium;" data-keep-original-tag="false" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}"><span style="font-family: helvetica;" data-keep-original-tag="false" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}">Hamilton, D., McKechnie, J., Edgerton, E., &amp; Wilson, C. (2021). Immersive virtual reality as a pedagogical tool in education: a systematic literature review of quantitative learning outcomes and experimental design. Journal of Computers in Education, 8(1), 1-32. </span></span></p>
<p data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}"><span style="font-size: medium;" data-keep-original-tag="false" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}"><span style="font-family: helvetica;" data-keep-original-tag="false" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}">Iacono, S., &amp; Vercelli, G. (2019). Lessons learned about language learning and extended reality frameworks. In the 5th International Conference on Virtual and Augmented Reality in Education (pp. 51-55).  <br></span></span></p>
<p data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}"><span style="font-size: medium;" data-keep-original-tag="false" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}"><span style="font-family: helvetica;" data-keep-original-tag="false" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}">Jelke, B., Tran, L., Wagner, L., &amp; Baus, L. (2022). Developing a trauma-informed interviewing training module prototype for law enforcement using virtual reality. Immersive Learning Research-Practitioner, 28-31.</span></span></p>
<p data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}"><span style="font-size: medium;" data-keep-original-tag="false" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}"><span style="font-family: helvetica;" data-keep-original-tag="false" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}">Kaplan, Alexandra D., Jessica Cruit, Mica Endsley, Suzanne M. Beers, Ben D. Sawyer, and Peter A. Hancock. "The effects of virtual reality, augmented reality, and mixed reality as training enhancement methods: A meta-analysis." Human factors 63, no. 4 (2021): 706-726.</span></span></p>
<p data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}"><span style="font-size: medium;" data-keep-original-tag="false" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}"><span style="font-family: helvetica;" data-keep-original-tag="false" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}">Lawson, A. P., &amp; Mayer, R. E. (2024). Effect of pre-training and role of working memory characteristics in learning with immersive virtual reality. International Journal of Human–Computer Interaction, 1-18. </span></span></p>
<p data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}"><span style="font-size: medium;" data-keep-original-tag="false" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}"><span style="font-family: helvetica;" data-keep-original-tag="false" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}">Lønne, T. F., Karlsen, H. R., Langvik, E., &amp; Saksvik-Lehouillier, I. (2023). The effect of immersion on sense of presence and affect when experiencing an educational scenario in virtual reality: A randomized controlled study. Heliyon, 9(6).  </span></span></p>
<p data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}"><span style="font-size: medium;" data-keep-original-tag="false" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}"><span style="font-family: helvetica;" data-keep-original-tag="false" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}">Markowitz, D. M., Bailenson, J. N., &amp; Markowitz, D. M. (2024, preprint) A looking glass into a research wonderland: 40 years of virtual reality scholarship explicated via natural language processing. <br></span></span></p>
<p data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}"><span style="font-size: medium;" data-keep-original-tag="false" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}"><span style="font-family: helvetica;" data-keep-original-tag="false" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}">Mathew, P. S., &amp; Pillai, A. S. (2020). Role of immersive (XR) technologies in improving healthcare competencies: a review. Virtual and augmented reality in education, art, and museums, 23-46. <br></span></span></p>
<p data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}"><span style="font-size: medium;" data-keep-original-tag="false" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}"><span style="font-family: helvetica;" data-keep-original-tag="false" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}">Murad, A. (2023, August 21). Virtual reality brings new vision to workplace training. BBC News. <a data-original-attrs="{&quot;data-original-href&quot;:&quot;https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/business-66393315.amp&quot;,&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}" href="https://draft.blogger.com/#">https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/business-66393315.amp</a></span></span></p>
<p data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}"><span style="font-size: medium;" data-keep-original-tag="false" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}"><span style="font-family: helvetica;" data-keep-original-tag="false" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}">Neelen, M. &amp; Kirschner, P. (2020). Truth or truthiness? Analysing a VR study using Gorard’s sieve. <a data-original-attrs="{&quot;data-original-href&quot;:&quot;https://3starlearningexperiences.wordpress.com/2020/07/07/truth-or-truthiness-analysing-a-vr-study-using-gorards-sieve/&quot;,&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;target&quot;:&quot;_blank&quot;}" href="https://draft.blogger.com/#" rel="nofollow">https://3starlearningexperiences.wordpress.com/2020/07/07/truth-or-truthiness-analysing-a-vr-study-using-gorards-sieve/</a> </span></span></p>
<p data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}"><span style="font-size: medium;" data-keep-original-tag="false" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}"><span style="font-family: helvetica;" data-keep-original-tag="false" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}">O'Dwyer, L. (2021). Review of employment-based training models. National Centre for Vocational Education Research (NCVER). <a data-original-attrs="{&quot;data-original-href&quot;:&quot;https://files.eric.ed.gov/fulltext/ED615316.pdf &quot;,&quot;target&quot;:&quot;_blank&quot;}" href="https://draft.blogger.com/#" rel="nofollow">https://files.eric.ed.gov/fulltext/ED615316.pdf </a></span></span></p>
<p data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}"><span style="font-size: medium;" data-keep-original-tag="false" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}"><span style="font-family: helvetica;" data-keep-original-tag="false" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}">Rode, R. &amp; Spasojevic, M. (2024, April 2). From XR pilots to full-scale deployments: considerations. Educause Review. <a data-original-attrs="{&quot;data-original-href&quot;:&quot;https://er.educause.edu/articles/2024/4/from-xr-pilots-to-full-scale-deployments-considerations&quot;,&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;target&quot;:&quot;_blank&quot;}" href="https://draft.blogger.com/#" rel="nofollow">https://er.educause.edu/articles/2024/4/from-xr-pilots-to-full-scale-deployments-considerations</a><u><span style="color: #2b00fe;" data-keep-original-tag="false" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}"><br></span></u></span></span></p>
<p data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}"><span style="font-size: medium;" data-keep-original-tag="false" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}"><span style="font-family: helvetica;" data-keep-original-tag="false" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}">Schwantes, M. (2020, July 22). 3 ways to train your workers: virtual reality, classroom, and e-Learning (One works best). Inc. <span style="color: #2b00fe;" data-keep-original-tag="false" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}"><a data-original-attrs="{&quot;data-original-href&quot;:&quot;https://www.inc.com/marcel-schwantes/how-to-train-your-workers-virtual-reality.html&quot;,&quot;target&quot;:&quot;_blank&quot;}" href="https://draft.blogger.com/#" rel="nofollow">https://www.inc.com/marcel-schwantes/how-to-train-your-workers-virtual-reality.html</a></span></span></span></p>
<p data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}"><span style="font-size: medium;" data-keep-original-tag="false" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}"><span style="font-family: helvetica;" data-keep-original-tag="false" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}">VictoryXR. (2024). About us. <a data-original-attrs="{&quot;data-original-href&quot;:&quot;https://www.victoryxr.com/about-us/&quot;}" href="https://draft.blogger.com/#"><span style="color: #2b00fe;" data-keep-original-tag="false" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}"><i>https://www.victoryxr.com/about-us/</i></span></a></span></span></p>
<p data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}"><span style="font-size: medium;" data-keep-original-tag="false" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}"><span style="font-family: helvetica;" data-keep-original-tag="false" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}">Zielinski, D. (2021). The growing impact of virtual reality training. </span></span></p>
<hr>
<p>Did you miss the other parts of this series? Here they are!</p>
<p><strong><a href="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/part-1-from-myths-to-principles-navigating-instructional-design-in-immersive-environments.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Part 1: From Myths To Principles: Navigating Instructional Design in Immersive Environments</a></strong></p>
<p><strong><a href="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/part-2-the-immersive-environment-delusion.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Part 2: The Immersive Environment Delusion</a></strong></p>
<p><strong><a href="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/part-3-the-case-against-virtual-campuses.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Part 3: The Case Against Virtual Campuses</a></strong></p>
<p><strong><a href="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/part-4-myth-learners-learn-faster.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Part 4: Myth: Learners Learn Faster</a></strong></p>
<p><strong><a href="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/part-5-myth-learners-learn-more.html">Part 5: Myth: Learners Learn More<br><br></a><a href="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/part-6-myth-immersive-learning-is-active-learning.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Part 6: Myth: Immersive learning is active learning</a></strong></p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Part 4 Myth: Learners learn faster</title>
        <author>
            <name>Heather Dodds</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/part-4-myth-learners-learn-faster.html"/>
        <id>https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/part-4-myth-learners-learn-faster.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/724/XR-does-not-cause-faster-learning1.png" medium="image" />

        <updated>2024-11-12T14:32:00-05:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/724/XR-does-not-cause-faster-learning1.png" alt="" />
                    Dispelling Myths With some background established on boom and bust cycles in the hype for immersive experiences (Parts 1, 2, and 3), we need to dismiss the rather rampant myths about learning within immersive experiences. In the hype, learning advantages have been overstated and over&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/724/XR-does-not-cause-faster-learning1.png" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <h1 style="text-align: left;">Dispelling Myths</h1>
<p>With some background established on boom and bust cycles in the hype for immersive experiences (Parts <a href="https://heatheredodds.blogspot.com/2024/10/from-myths-to-principles-navigating.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">1</a>, <a href="https://heatheredodds.blogspot.com/2024/10/the-immersive-environment-delusion-part.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2</a>, and <a href="https://heatheredodds.blogspot.com/2024/11/part-3-case-against-virtual-campuses.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">3</a>), we need to dismiss the rather rampant myths about learning within immersive experiences. In the hype, learning advantages have been overstated and over simplified. Web pages post outrageous claims (and I’ll show you!). Keynote presentations banty incredible promises (yup, it was recorded). This series addresses the four primary myths about learning within immersive experiences: that is, that it is faster, greater, active, and induces empathy. <br><br>In this Part 4, I’ll address the “learners learn faster in immersive experiences” myth. For those of you that follow my writing, you’ll know that this is Round 3 of me taking on this myth. My argument has not changed; remember this article series is an update, but not every point needs updating. However, I continue to communicate about this because the “VR learning is faster” myth continues to circulate– mostly in the reference to “4 times faster” and the PwC report. So, TLDR, the VR experience was designed to be 29 minutes long. That’s it. No longer. The classroom equivalent in content experience was designed to be 2 hours long. That’s it. 29 minutes is ¼ of 120 minutes. Someone inverted ¼ to 4x (which is factually true) and PwC who appears to have had a cozy contract with Oculus/Meta at the time, went out to trumpet the ‘four times’ from the rooftops. But students do NOT learn faster. They experienced a learning event that was designed to be faster. Had the learners spent 120 minutes in the headset, someone would have probably greedily snatched the headset off their heads and told them that they overstayed their welcome (and wondered what they were doing for the extra 91 minutes).</p>
<h2 style="text-align: left;">Myth: Learners learn faster in immersive experiences</h2>
<p>The first myth asserts that learners learn faster with immersive experiences. Particularly, the phrase “four times faster” has taken root in the publications and in public discourse. A google search on the phrase “VR is 4 times faster” returns a plethora of results repeating the myth.</p>
<p> </p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://lh7-rt.googleusercontent.com/docsz/AD_4nXePp9VIySOLd742WIX8bRGFeUNxKGf2v6bXZ63TuZI1xa56zdkbfAyDAlfDpRfI2i_IBXP8b9b0FmIsZUldjnreXcq3vyBTqvyWx9zwuZLRRXwYKF8WAi-LrOV-ncHhb4hrGM084w=w400-h54?key=KhzE38av9NusmLLt_1haAg" data-is-external-image="true"><figcaption>4x in the wild. And it's not hard to catch, yo.</figcaption></figure>
<p><br>The source of this phrase is suggested to be one non-peer reviewed industry report by PricewaterhouseCooper. Within the report, VR-based learning was “4x faster than classroom training on average” (Eckert &amp; Mower, 2020, p. 8). The results of this report were then repeated in academic literature.</p>
<table class="tr-caption-container" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="0" align="center" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}">
<tbody>
<tr>
<td data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}"><img loading="lazy" src="https://lh7-rt.googleusercontent.com/docsz/AD_4nXerlmydNry9qvRIRHZaA3kJH8bG101Ci4R59hf4GFhKT38xVtFKuJJQuQ2ZSZCaSt_IE0yBNUE95OapLL-ZxqDX6xD0OjPReS8Eqx1ZDhxfGtS39uiG7_wEqzLLdg7cL2IcaDsu8Q=w640-h506?key=KhzE38av9NusmLLt_1haAg" alt="Pie graph showing classroom training took 2 hours, e-learning training took 45 minutes, and VR training took 29 minutes. Text: We were able to train employees up to four times faster in VR than in the classroom and 1.5 times faster than e-learn." width="640" height="506" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}" data-is-external-image="true"></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="tr-caption" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}">Do not make pie graphs that do not add up to one whole thing.</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>Referring to the same report, D. Clark (an educational researcher not known for getting data wrong, but he did) wrote enthusiastically that “VR was x4 faster than classroom and x1.5 faster than e-learning” (2021, p. 190). Claims that learning is completed faster attempt to represent immersive experiences as a more efficient learning method, i.e., less time to learn equals learning faster.</p>
<p><br>Tracking down how many academic papers have cited the PwC report is difficult. I've seen numbers as little as 4 citations and much higher numbers if I start flexing my search. Part of the problem is that folks have not cited the report (even though it calls itself a study) correctly. Some credit PwC, a few find the Eckert and Mower authors, but in general the hand wave approach to referring to the 4x data is very prevalent.</p>
<p><br><br>The cause of this supposed faster learning was attributed to how a VR headset isolates the learner’s perception, so that the learner is focused on the learning task at hand. In other words, less distraction equals more focus. In the PricewaterhouseCooper report, Likens seemed to hypothesize that, “A lot of courses that normally take an hour could be completed in 20 minutes through VR because people are so immersed in scenarios, there are fewer distractions and the learning is very concentrated” (Zielinski, 2021, para. 10). <br><br>To be clear, in the PwC case, classroom learning which covered the same content was designed to take two hours to complete. The immersive experience was designed to take 29 minutes. Given that 29 minutes is approximately one-quarter of two hours, PwC inverted the time ratio and touted the line that the immersive learning was four times faster. The problem is that it is not true that learning in the immersive experience was faster. The VR-based learning took less time because it was designed to be a 29-minute one-on-one learning experience designed for a shorter total time duration. When compared to classroom learning, it is already known that one-on-one personalized learning is generally faster; it moves at the speed of the learner, not at the speed of the class. Perhaps, this is how myths begin. A kernel of truth gets extended to something with no context. Lack of context is a noted and rising problem in educational research (Williamson, 2024).<br><br>Learning faster can be confused with greater efficiency. Efficiency could have a wide range of meanings beyond just taking less time. It could also mean wiser use of resources or less teaching burden on the instructor. Another example of the loose wordplay is on an industry webpage that displayed that VR training was 50% faster than a traditional in-person medical simulation. Not stated in the distilled summary of that study is that <em>learners scored worse in the VR training than the traditional</em> in-person medical simulation (Katz et al., 2020).</p>
<p> </p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEi_AX7u9zAKkVEVWvNRatDZCU36qUVet1bcNkBQSYAdvWAdwZaQ81zLrQvOOGZyAhfYiNpiylwij-lrDmndRuWy5T_OJKJ0wWcMA75uD6YJaYUk8KIgUrJKGruDmNSnljnf7cT_ohpnSPJB1wMrH3UxlojRm8SMlvXXfMBCSRn4gvBPxiAt9n4aaAbzFD4/w640-h72/capture%20from%20Katz%20Gary%20paper.png" border="0" data-is-external-image="true"><figcaption>If faster equals worse performance, this might not be the efficiency that educators are looking for.</figcaption></figure>
<p><br><br>The myth that learning happens faster continues when educators fail to acknowledge that a different instructional method was being used. When supporting using virtual reality for chemistry studies, Muhsinah Morris, a chemistry professor and metaverse program director at Morehouse said “You can’t see molecules, but in my virtual reality classroom where I taught advanced inorganic chemistry, you can. You can actually build three-dimensional representations of molecules … The learning tends to happen faster. They go on to the real situation faster.” (D’Agostino, 2022, para. 5).</p>
<h2 style="text-align: left;">Side point: Learning Chemistry in Three Dimensions</h2>
<p>Since this is my publishing space, I am going to spend some time on Mushinah Morris’ instructional and learning point here. Again, I was involved in the online teaching of chemistry for 14 years and my research speciality was science in VR, so I’ve got thoughts. If you would like to see her talk on video on this, she’s in <a href="https://youtu.be/F3bQ4Aw3Vis?si=JuJ4QvIQS9X5USCJ&amp;t=70" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer">this VictoryXR video</a>.<br><br>She is correct that molecules cannot currently be seen in everyday life. It makes chemistry, as a field, a more abstract or conceptual field (along with physics) when compared to the “you can see it before you” fields of biology or earth science. Teaching that something unseen exists and engages in reactions has always been the uphill battle of chemistry teachers. So she’s describing an accurate problem. <br><br>There is a tiny fly in the ointment, however, in that not many students at the college level fall into a chemistry course completely unfamiliar with chemistry at all. So learners in college chemistry probably were exposed to atoms in some other prior learning experience, be it high school, a museum, or a summer-camp like situation. So do her students need to learn atoms from the very beginning? I somewhat doubt that. </p>
<h3 style="text-align: left;">HCHE Advanced Inorganic Chemistry</h3>
<p>To massively further complicate her argument, she names and shows her chemistry course “Advanced Inorganic Chemistry”. That’s HCHE 421 at Morehouse University, which in 2021 had a prerequisite: <br><br>HCHE 322 Elementary Physical Chemistry,</p>
<p>which itself has 3 prerequisites: <br><br>CHE 321/321L, Elementary Physical Chemistry and Lab (which has 4 prereqs: CHE 232, PHY 154, and MTH 161 and 162)<br><br>PHY 253 Electricity &amp; Magnetism, which has 2 prerequisites: PHY 154 (C or better) and MTH 162<br><br>MTH 271 Introduction to Linear Algebra, which has 1 prerequisite: MTH 161 <br><br>You see where I’m going here.</p>
<p>It’s highly doubtful that students arriving in an advanced chemistry class after what is <i>years at college</i>, whose content focus is actually math (that’s what inorganic focuses on) and not spatial abilities (which arguably organic chemistry DOES focus on) have a substantial problem with visualizing atoms and molecules to the point where it is disturbing their learning performance. And therefore VR could make a difference. No. Not buying it. </p>
<table class="tr-caption-container" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="0" align="center" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}">
<tbody>
<tr>
<td data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}"><a data-original-attrs="{&quot;data-original-href&quot;:&quot;https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEhhJjCl7c-vT66UHrARpdc_gib7AWxv0aFb1YPKD-jNDOrSs6XkvO2BvG77w0nO0SLb2zYEDcA58o3_1gBKXl68pTBZkmp0Vm39WO2AXOwxS42-xbk5t736UVo-IBrTfVwxZIHGuhUKcDSLgST6-4kD-B5L4eZ-ywEC0fAg9xeYd1BtXGBeKOMj1mP0Sr4/s1824/electrical%20potential%20lab.PNG&quot;,&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}" href="https://draft.blogger.com/#"><img loading="lazy" src="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEhhJjCl7c-vT66UHrARpdc_gib7AWxv0aFb1YPKD-jNDOrSs6XkvO2BvG77w0nO0SLb2zYEDcA58o3_1gBKXl68pTBZkmp0Vm39WO2AXOwxS42-xbk5t736UVo-IBrTfVwxZIHGuhUKcDSLgST6-4kD-B5L4eZ-ywEC0fAg9xeYd1BtXGBeKOMj1mP0Sr4/w640-h422/electrical%20potential%20lab.PNG" width="640" height="422" border="0" data-original-height="1203" data-original-width="1824" data-is-external-image="true"></a></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="tr-caption" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}">Covered in the mentioned course's lab. That's math, yo.</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p><br>Nonetheless, I’ve known very smart people have trouble visualizing atoms. So it IS remotely possible and let’s pretend she is articulating only the beginning of the trouble of understanding for a lay crowd…not the only problem. Said another way, she's speaking about VR's affordances overall, maybe not specifically for her students in her aforementioned class. For example, some chemical reactions are easy to understand (like cooking) and some are difficult to understand (like how hair coloring works or cell electrical potentials).<br><br>It is interesting that she said “The learning tends to happen faster.” It’s a couched statement, for sure, with the word “tends”. In science that cannot be pinned down. So she gave herself an out. But what was she describing? At this point, we have to think about the instruction of chemistry.</p>
<h3 style="text-align: left;">How To Show Atoms and Molecules</h3>
<p>Within the history of chemistry itself is the continuing saga of how will atoms be depicted? As in, how do you draw them? How are they really? And how does a teacher relay that ‘realness’ to the learners– and why? </p>
<p>So we’ve had our:</p>
<p>Atoms are indivisible tiny units, folks. <a href="https://chem.libretexts.org/Bookshelves/Introductory_Chemistry/Chemistry_for_Changing_Times_(Hill_and_McCreary)/02%3A_Atoms/2.01%3A_Atoms_-_Ideas_from_the_Ancient_Greeks">Thank you to the Greeks</a>! There are no pictures from that time.</p>
<p>We’ve had Bohr’s heliocentric-like model folks wherein the atom looks like a solar system or set of concentric rings. To be fair, the heliocentric model really does help explain things like electron energy levels.</p>
<p> </p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEjB00rew0oTEEdBhPv5JrxR-UQSx0Am1dlAwqgJboXOn_NtBQUZU4YLChGmGgdU98W5m3JRb9jo_muJ-FEvSj9wUHlyAbeDSETcaLInVvmVeSRlzon4DjAlMvCIOGdso0XeOJD3oPI_aEA4CWfK0hz5yCgKKmqTrvQ-iU7RQVwd76tlct5JsGXzRFfSyPc/w400-h141/bohr%20model.png" border="0" data-is-external-image="true"><figcaption>Bhor's heliocentric-like atomic model</figcaption></figure>
<p><br>We’ve had our Thomson plum pudding folks– which never translated from its culture. Which is probably a shame. I like plums.</p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEiVgn22KNTjuudLWm0L9MzuJ2O26K_9SY8GYDN4PSoeIUlztvF0e8jD3sUXDpcvqYQuJpel4RGOULljzOIaJUBE28xAdP37IVYbppmCrOC5ZmHL8xw7y9-dVRnZRHnos049QjKMsUOxHuSe8Rr1opzXbOJyq4mwbY7eFrLOoROqUAvX3GZt66KMrIU5mz4/w320-h117/plum%20pudding%20model.png" border="0" data-is-external-image="true"><figcaption>Thompson's plum pudding atomic model.</figcaption></figure>
<p> </p>
<p>We’ve had our ‘cloud model’ folks - which are like the postmodern philosophers of chemistry. Truth for me, truth for you, we all get a truth. Which isn’t <em>actually</em> true. But they told us that electrons cannot be pinned down and measured, they could be anywhere at any time but when we set about measuring them, that’s when they run away from us. Yes, I’m nodding to Heisenberg here. And wave/particle theory.</p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEibpJhvPiUq6dUB_5YtuQDvewBFwmWmaatUZaeCm_LDXSJ_9RcU3HZQ_19lsf70Yt8fO3wV00L0I7h7qcjsLcv3OGEp3WBeZBiUBDa-Pgyq7QVJZ3ccIS_czFNctafILtLeceAvTO2smQ3tsxJoMJAO8EaXdjiHR3s7Lq6ITOXF3eRsw02pa0lMiyV6Boo/w320-h133/Screenshot%202024-11-11%20095220.png" alt="Cloud model of what an atom looks like." width="320" height="133" border="0" data-original-height="285" data-original-width="685" data-is-external-image="true"><figcaption>Cloud model of what an atom looks like.</figcaption></figure>
<p>After the heliocentric model, however, depictions of atoms needed to be displayed as three-dimensional, not just as two-dimensional on flat paper. By far, I’ve only selected some of the atomic model theories here. If you want to know more, study chemistry! It’s not hard.<br><br>But, now, going against Mushinah Morris’ arguments now, educators HAVE been working on that educational problem for years (with success, mind you).</p>
<p>First of all, delightful molecular (and atom) kits exist with physical manipulatives. Yeah, they look like tinker toys.  I love them. They are good for at least 30 minutes of instruction, maybe more. They are usually plastic (boo, although there is nothing stopping them from being made of wood) and the kits would have to be purchased, stored, and de-germed from time to time. So they have their minor downsides.</p>
<p>Second of all, 2D screens can show 3D objects…that’s entirely possible.</p>
<p>Third, programming VR to follow mathematical principles – like, voila, chemistry DOES!-- is actually not that hard. The first uses of VR in education that I know of were in the “physical”---that is mathematical sciences, physics and chemistry. Let’s face it. A computer understands 9.8 meters per second per second MUCH easier than a person does. (&lt;- that’s one gravitational force).<br><br><br>And get this, purchasing a simulation to teach atoms is so drop-dead cheap that it’s actually <a href="https://phet.colorado.edu/">free </a>by now. I have recommended those simulations for courses before and seen learning scores do quite well, thank you. </p>
<table class="tr-caption-container" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="0" align="center" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}">
<tbody>
<tr>
<td data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}"><a data-original-attrs="{&quot;data-original-href&quot;:&quot;https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEhQ4VRHRuhnk_umAovu7u9r1CRNvXCwOkXzz0qxfYrmTv8KL6Mcb7YJM4uwlLGyb8ihy73oRzVvLtJvrZr2CjSFtpLXD1EzddYEhyphenhyphenY3OJxOxpDwEx77DXuH5rwSrZs0QBZKRWjXLhEveRczbEq8-7AmgjcgE5xIFGOA3YeNf7i8H5rySGRKlVSOJTEpYiY/s426/Phet%203d%20for%20free%20-%20Made%20with%20Clipchamp.gif&quot;,&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}" href="https://draft.blogger.com/#"><img loading="lazy" src="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEhQ4VRHRuhnk_umAovu7u9r1CRNvXCwOkXzz0qxfYrmTv8KL6Mcb7YJM4uwlLGyb8ihy73oRzVvLtJvrZr2CjSFtpLXD1EzddYEhyphenhyphenY3OJxOxpDwEx77DXuH5rwSrZs0QBZKRWjXLhEveRczbEq8-7AmgjcgE5xIFGOA3YeNf7i8H5rySGRKlVSOJTEpYiY/s320/Phet%203d%20for%20free%20-%20Made%20with%20Clipchamp.gif" width="320" height="180" border="0" data-original-height="240" data-original-width="426" data-is-external-image="true"></a></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="tr-caption" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}">Looks pretty 3D to me</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p><br>I seriously bet that if I had been able to place that counter proposal before her administrators, I’d win the budget proposal. Ha! Bonus points that I could prove that my students would score equal to her VR students on the final exam.<br><br>So in all, did she make a good point here? I’d say no but that’s because I recognize the instructional problem and I realize that the problem can be solved in a much cheaper and equally as efficient way. Also, she showed no data that “the learners learned faster”.<br><br>Side point to the side point: Mushinah Morris on YouTube is highly associated with VictoryXR, the vendor that she is using when referring to her VR-for-education accomplishments. Close association with XR vendors makes for suspicious conclusions. I'm not picking on Mushinah Morris unfairly. She's gone on the record multiple times for her claims. I could easily pick (and will in the future) other education influencers that are selling the VR-for-education snake oil.<br><br>Back to my article<br><br><br>Further, there is at least one study (so far!) that refutes this focusing-causes-faster-learning claim. Makransky, Terkildsen, et al. (2019) found that immersive metaverse environments could be sensory overload for learners and therefore decrease the learner’s focus. On the whole, claims for increased speed can often be attributed to more efficient instructional methods. Immersive experiences can allow for the utilization of comparatively faster instructional methods.<br><br>The author finds this myth, that immersive experiences cause learners to learn faster, false. </p>
<hr>
<h3 style="text-align: left;">References</h3>
<p> </p>
<p dir="ltr" style="line-height: 1.44; margin-bottom: 0pt; margin-top: 6pt;">Clark, D. (2021). Learning experience design: How to create effective learning that works. Kogan Page Publishers.<br><br>D’Agostino, S. (2022, August 3). College in the metaverse is here. Is higher ed ready? Inside Higher Ed | Higher Education News, Events and Jobs. <a href="https://www.insidehighered.com/news/2022/08/03/college-metaverse-here-higher-ed-ready">https://www.insidehighered.com/news/2022/08/03/college-metaverse-here-higher-ed-ready</a><br><br>Eckert, D., &amp; Mower, A. (2020). The effectiveness of virtual reality soft skills training in the enterprise: a study. PwC Public Report. <a href="https://www.pwc.com/us/en/services/consulting/technology/emerging-technology/assets/pwc-understanding-the-effectiveness-of-soft-skills-training-in-the-enterprise-a-study.pdf">https://www.pwc.com/us/en/services/consulting/technology/emerging-technology/assets/pwc-understanding-the-effectiveness-of-soft-skills-training-in-the-enterprise-a-study.pdf</a><br><br>Katz, D., Shah, R., Kim, E., Park, C., Shah, A., Levine, A., &amp; Burnett, G. (2020). Utilization of a Voice-Based Virtual Reality Advanced Cardiac Life Support Team Leader Refresher: Prospective Observational Study. Journal of Medical Internet Research, 22(3), e17425. https://doi.org/10.2196/17425<br><br>Makransky, G., Terkildsen, T. S., &amp; Mayer, R. E. (2019). Adding immersive virtual reality to a science lab simulation causes more presence but less learning. Learning and Instruction, 60, 225–236. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.learninstruc.2017.12.007">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.learninstruc.2017.12.007</a><br><br>Williamson, B., Macgilchrist, F., &amp; Potter, J. (2024). Against contextlessness in learning, media and technology. Learning, Media and Technology, 49(3), 335–338. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1080/17439884.2024.2374266">https://doi.org/10.1080/17439884.2024.2374266</a><br><br>Zielinski, D. (2021). The growing impact of virtual reality training. <a href="https://www.shrm.org/hr-today/news/hr-magazine/spring2021/pages/virtual-reality-training-spreads-its-wings.aspx">https://www.shrm.org/hr-today/news/hr-magazine/spring2021/pages/virtual-reality-training-spreads-its-wings.aspx<br></a></p>
<p dir="ltr" style="line-height: 1.44; margin-bottom: 0pt; margin-top: 6pt;"> </p>
<hr>
<p>Did you miss the other parts of this series? Here they are!</p>
<p><strong><a href="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/part-1-from-myths-to-principles-navigating-instructional-design-in-immersive-environments.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Part 1: From Myths To Principles: Navigating Instructional Design in Immersive Environments</a></strong></p>
<p><strong><a href="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/part-2-the-immersive-environment-delusion.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Part 2: The Immersive Environment Delusion</a></strong></p>
<p><strong><a href="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/part-3-the-case-against-virtual-campuses.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Part 3: The Case Against Virtual Campuses</a></strong></p>
<p><strong><a href="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/part-4-myth-learners-learn-faster.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Part 4: Myth: Learners Learn Faster</a></strong></p>
<p><strong><a href="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/part-5-myth-learners-learn-more.html">Part 5: Myth: Learners Learn More<br><br></a><a href="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/part-6-myth-immersive-learning-is-active-learning.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Part 6: Myth: Immersive learning is active learning</a></strong></p>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Part 3: The Case Against Virtual Campuses</title>
        <author>
            <name>Heather Dodds</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/part-3-the-case-against-virtual-campuses.html"/>
        <id>https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/part-3-the-case-against-virtual-campuses.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/725/cComparison-virtual-campus.png" medium="image" />

        <updated>2024-11-04T16:00:00-05:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/725/cComparison-virtual-campus.png" alt="" />
                    I write this title with a tinge of irony. I’ve owned virtual campuses. I’ve worked on virtual campuses. If asked to work on a virtual campus again, I’d likely say yes. So what’s my beef with virtual campuses? I feel that a sober-eyed look at&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/725/cComparison-virtual-campus.png" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <p class="article-editor-content__paragraph"><span style="font-family: arial;">I write this title with a tinge of irony. I’ve owned virtual campuses. I’ve worked on virtual campuses. If asked to work on a virtual campus again, I’d likely say yes.  So what’s my beef with virtual campuses? </span></p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph"><span style="font-family: arial;">I feel that a sober-eyed look at virtual campuses* is necessary.</span></p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph"><span style="font-family: arial;">Following the philosophy of “those who cannot remember the past are condemned to repeat it” (Santayana), here is Part 3 of my series: From Myths to Principles; Navigating Instructional Design in Immersive Environments.</span></p>
<h2 class="article-editor-content__heading" style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-family: arial;">The rise and fall of the metaversity</span></h2>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph"><span style="font-family: arial;">In <a class="article-editor-content__link article-editor-content__link" href="https://heatheredodds.blogspot.com/2024/10/the-immersive-environment-delusion-part.html" rel="noopener noreferrer">Part 2</a> of this series,I examined two examples from the history of immersive learning. First, I showed the parallels when companies like Meta and Linden Lab dominate a single platform for immersive learning designs. The lesson is that what is allowed one day can quickly become disallowed the next day. Second, I pointed out the inappropriate boasting and poor course design used in the “first course in virtual reality” by Stanford University. In these recent cases (Meta and Stanford University) there was a remarkable lack of awareness of the history of immersive learning. Said another way, mistakes of the past were repeated.</span></p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph"><span style="font-family: arial;">In another example of history repeating itself, ten colleges and universities adopted digital twin campuses in June 2022 using the ENGAGE platform with monetary support and donated VR headsets from Meta (Koenig, 2022). These metaversity locations recreated (or <a class="article-editor-content__link article-editor-content__link" href="https://sway.cloud.microsoft/RyZEZBkthFHDhku7?ref=Link" rel="noopener noreferrer">created</a>!) campus buildings to allow learners to gather on the virtual campus. </span></p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph"><span style="font-family: arial;">Eight years prior, Second Life (SL) campus buildings were “designed to mimic real-world architectural equivalents” but had become “abandoned ghost towns” (Wecker, 2014). </span></p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph"><span style="font-family: arial;">The early Second Life virtual campus creations were often the result of student projects. Confusingly, the professors who designed and assigned these projects touted the work of creating faithful campus recreations as <i>creative</i> and thus, at the highest level of Bloom’s cognitive learning objectives. I’m inserting a heavy eye roll here because that’s really stretching the justification of working in virtual reality to an extreme point.  Plus, I have to point out: what does next year’s class build if this year’s class made the campus?  My point is that simply building campus buildings (so that you can have a virtual campus!) is a project idea that runs out of steam. Things got really interesting right after the SL virtual campuses were launched.  Everyone involved noticed that the spaces were not being utilized. </span></p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph"> </p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph"><span style="font-family: arial;">Students were asked why they weren't visiting the virtual campus.  </span></p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph"><span style="font-family: arial;">The answer was simple.</span></p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph"><span style="font-family: arial;">No one was there. </span></p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph"><span style="font-family: arial;">You see, you could have the most amazing design with all of the bells and whistles (really!), but if people were not there, then people found that there was no compelling reason to return. Admissions folks had no compelling reason to be in the virtual admissions building, same for financial aid teams. Even library teams today in virtual reality struggle to staff spaces with the same spread as IRL (in real life) libraries.</span></p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph"><span style="font-family: arial;">During a recent tour of the University of Maryland Global Campus metaversity campus, the audio connection failed. The host did not offer any tech support. The experience showcased empty buildings during what was a busy time of the academic semester. To be fair, I understand the implications of FERPA which might have predicted that students were in classroom spaces separate from public spaces. However, it is logical that on any campus, students could still be found  in public space buildings like the networking lounge. These accurate campus recreations rarely spur more than a passing interest to learners. </span></p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph is-empty" aria-label="Write here. You can also include @mentions."><span style="font-family: arial;"> </span></p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph"><span style="font-family: arial;">The ten colleges and universities in this project are now facing the end of the project and the initial funding is ending. Steven Van Hook commented that, “Administrators may speak of their twin campuses in glittering terms on the record –then off the record talk about their regrets and what else they could have bought for the hundreds of thousands of dollars” (VWBPE, 2024). According to Temple University’s Kathy Hirsh Pasek, “A year ago, a lot of companies were going full steam ahead. Today’s that’s not true; they’ve rerouted a lot of their funds for AI and Twitter alternatives” (Coffey, 2023, para. 37) Institutions made the decision to adopt immersive experiences but do not appear to know how to make wise decisions when generous funding stops and societal attention moves on.</span></p>
<h2 class="article-editor-content__heading" style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-family: arial;">The key problems</span></h2>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph"><span style="font-family: arial;">Therefore, throughout these first three parts of this series, there are several challenges apparent. Instructional designers and administrators must wade through the myriad of claims derived from dubious research studies. It feels like chicanery to figure out which statements about immersive experiences for learning are authentic and do point the way to future positive outcomes and which statements are in doubt. The first issue is with interpreting research wisely. Every research study has inherent flaws; no one study can definitively provide answers to all of education’s questions. This situation is made worse when the research is translated into social media and seems to tout incredible claims (Lanier et al., 2019).</span></p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph"><span style="font-family: arial;">Therefore, the conundrum has been illuminated. The myths that appear to come from a research basis must be dispelled. Next, the very basis of the published research record is at risk of bias and problems. This series will inform on what characteristics to look for in published research.  Finally, if one were to step around the research interpretation problems, what is the system for building and using immersive experiences for its best advantage? This series will attempt to answer these questions. This series then forms the navigator role for instructional designers and administrators figuring out how to chart a route to a successful implementation. </span></p>
<p class="article-editor-content__heading"><span style="font-family: arial;">Post Script</span></p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph"><span style="font-family: arial;">*virtual campuses </span></p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph"><span style="font-family: arial;">I’m using the term virtual campuses to specifically refer to real world recreations of campus spaces like quads and lecture halls. I am not referring to simulations (for example in science courses) or spaces specifically designed for social use (for example, dance halls). </span></p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph"><span style="font-family: arial;">Virtual campuses were designed as early as 1999 as text-based educational MUVEs (multi user virtual environments). This example classroom shows “the room’s description, list of contents, who  is in the room, the exits, and links to applications” (Maher, et al., 1999).</span></p>
<table class="tr-caption-container" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="0" align="center" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}">
<tbody>
<tr>
<td data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}"><a data-original-attrs="{&quot;data-original-href&quot;:&quot;https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEicBQ_V172tE1VTKHUpE6e_HrHL2TD8fj4H3_p-P_BdFI37I4UXjqVa-7_bkyvyxT7jRn-jkowazPknq7iuOduLeT_W5IZk1r668Z5Iwqe9FC1nkmejAn6ggkJpjow4lxVc22QS_QhGz_A01Oq7h2U-LwVsMfrbisxooYHJIFUH0CUzYipRALqehLuOyiE/s717/theory%20and%20practice%20room%20at%20the%20university%20of%20syndey%201999.png&quot;,&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}" href="https://draft.blogger.com/#"><img loading="lazy" src="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEicBQ_V172tE1VTKHUpE6e_HrHL2TD8fj4H3_p-P_BdFI37I4UXjqVa-7_bkyvyxT7jRn-jkowazPknq7iuOduLeT_W5IZk1r668Z5Iwqe9FC1nkmejAn6ggkJpjow4lxVc22QS_QhGz_A01Oq7h2U-LwVsMfrbisxooYHJIFUH0CUzYipRALqehLuOyiE/s320/theory%20and%20practice%20room%20at%20the%20university%20of%20syndey%201999.png" width="320" height="291" border="0" data-original-height="653" data-original-width="717" data-is-external-image="true"></a></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="tr-caption" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}"><span style="font-family: arial;" data-keep-original-tag="false" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}">Technically, 'Nobody else is here' might have been foresight.</span></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p><span style="font-family: arial;"><br><br>The metaversity concept is not to be confused with metauniversities, which are global collaborating universities (Costanza, et al., 2021). It appears as though the metaversity term became popular in 2021 and the company ENGAGE is not the only entity to claim it.</span></p>
<h2><span style="font-family: arial;"><br>References</span></h2>
<p><span style="font-family: arial;"><br><br>Coffey, L. (2023, July 11). “Metaversities” face virtual learning’s financial reality. Inside Higher Ed | Higher Education News, Events and Jobs.<a href="https://www.insidehighered.com/news/tech-innovation/teaching-learning/2023/07/11/metaversities-face-virtual-learnings-financial"> https://www.insidehighered.com/news/tech-innovation/teaching-learning/2023/07/11/metaversities-face-virtual-learnings-financial</a><br><br>Costanza, R., Kubiszewski, I., Kompas, T., &amp; Sutton, P. C. (2021). A global metauniversity to lead by design to a sustainable well-being future. Frontiers in Sustainability, 2, 653721.<br><br>Koenig, R. (2022, June 6). With Money From Facebook, 10 Colleges Turn Their Campuses into ‘Metaversities.’ EdSurge.<a href="https://www.edsurge.com/news/2022-06-01-with-money-from-facebook-10-colleges-turn-their-campuses-into-metaversities"> https://www.edsurge.com/news/2022-06-01-with-money-from-facebook-10-colleges-turn-their-campuses-into-metaversities</a><br><br>Lanier, M., Waddell, T. F., Elson, M., Tamul, D. J., Ivory, J. D., &amp; Przybylski, A. (2019). Virtual reality check: Statistical power, reported results, and the validity of research on the psychology of virtual reality and immersive environments. Computers in Human Behavior, 100, 70–78.<a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chb.2019.06.015"> https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chb.2019.06.015</a><br><br>Maher, M. L., Skow, B., &amp; Cicognani, A. (1999). Designing the virtual campus. Design Studies, 20(4), 319-342.<br><br>Wecker, M. (2014, April 22). What ever happened to Second Life? Chronicle Vitae.<a href="https://chroniclevitae.com/news/456-what-ever-happened-to-second-life"> https://chroniclevitae.com/news/456-what-ever-happened-to-second-life</a><br><br>#VirtualCampus #edtech #VirtualUniversity<br><br></span></p>
<hr>
<p>Did you miss the other parts of this series? Here they are!</p>
<p><strong><a href="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/part-1-from-myths-to-principles-navigating-instructional-design-in-immersive-environments.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Part 1: From Myths To Principles: Navigating Instructional Design in Immersive Environments</a></strong></p>
<p><strong><a href="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/part-2-the-immersive-environment-delusion.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Part 2: The Immersive Environment Delusion</a></strong></p>
<p><strong><a href="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/part-3-the-case-against-virtual-campuses.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Part 3: The Case Against Virtual Campuses</a></strong></p>
<p><strong><a href="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/part-4-myth-learners-learn-faster.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Part 4: Myth: Learners Learn Faster</a></strong></p>
<p><strong><a href="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/part-5-myth-learners-learn-more.html">Part 5: Myth: Learners Learn More<br><br></a><a href="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/part-6-myth-immersive-learning-is-active-learning.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Part 6: Myth: Immersive learning is active learning</a></strong></p>
<p><span style="font-family: arial;"> </span><br><a href="https://heatheredodds.blogspot.com/2025/01/part-6-myth-immersive-learning-is.html"></a></p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph is-empty article-editor-content__has-focus" aria-label="Write here. You can also include @mentions."> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Part 2: The Immersive Environment Delusion</title>
        <author>
            <name>Heather Dodds</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/part-2-the-immersive-environment-delusion.html"/>
        <id>https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/part-2-the-immersive-environment-delusion.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/726/The-computer-delusion-in-a-sci-fi-retrofuturism-style-smaller-in-scale-more-personal-with-jazzy-elements-no-text.png" medium="image" />

        <updated>2024-10-06T21:32:00-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/726/The-computer-delusion-in-a-sci-fi-retrofuturism-style-smaller-in-scale-more-personal-with-jazzy-elements-no-text.png" alt="" />
                    In Part 1, we introduced this new series, From Myths to Principles: Navigating Instructional Design in Immersive Environments. This is an update from my 2023 series. In this Part 2, we're going to go through some backstory showing the educators in Second Life was the&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/726/The-computer-delusion-in-a-sci-fi-retrofuturism-style-smaller-in-scale-more-personal-with-jazzy-elements-no-text.png" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <p>In Part 1, we introduced this new series, From Myths to Principles: Navigating Instructional Design in Immersive Environments. This is an update from my 2023 series.<br><br>In this Part 2, we're going to go through some backstory showing the educators in Second Life was the first wave of hype for using immersive environments and we'll look at one recent example from Stanford University with their "<i>Virtual People</i>" course.<br><br>Here we go!</p>
<h1 id="docs-internal-guid-195a7ea9-7fff-f06d-26c5-8b3e4fa397e0" dir="ltr" style="line-height: 1.56; margin-bottom: 2pt; margin-top: 12pt;"><span style="background-color: transparent; color: blue; font-size: 18pt; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: bold; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline;">History repeats itself</span></h1>
<div id="docs-internal-guid-195a7ea9-7fff-f06d-26c5-8b3e4fa397e0" style="line-height: 1.56; margin-bottom: 2pt; margin-top: 12pt; text-align: left;"><span style="font-family: helvetica;">The history of educational technology is a rhyme that repeats. Initial pitches have created optimism that the next big thing in technology will revolutionize education. <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/archive/1997/07/the-computer-delusion/376899/">Oppenheimer</a> (1997) in a really well written article illustrated part of the history of educational technology by citing four examples:</span></div>
<div style="text-align: left;">
<ol style="text-align: left;">
<li><span style="font-family: helvetica;">Edison’s 1922 prediction that the motion picture will revolutionize education.</span></li>
<li><span style="font-family: helvetica;">Levenson’s claim that radios will become common in every classroom.</span></li>
<li><span style="font-family: helvetica;">Skinner asserted that learners with teaching machines could learn twice as much.</span></li>
<li><span style="font-family: helvetica;">Clinton campaigned that computers are a bridge to the twenty-first century. (para. 1)</span></li>
</ol>
<p><span style="font-family: helvetica;">The motion picture, the radio receiver, programmed instruction, and computers in the classroom have all failed to significantly impact learner performance. The past 102 years have not been kind to hyped educational technology predictions.</span></p>
</div>
<blockquote>
<div style="text-align: left;">I can hear you through the nether. <br>There are some saying "But the metaverse is different!" <br>Sit down. 👈😠<br>I'll deal with you soon enough.</div>
</blockquote>
<div style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-family: helvetica;"><br>Cuban (1986) further suggested that this educational technology adoption cycle follows a predictable pattern. First, the earliest research will be produced by the technology producers themselves. Second, problems arise with adoption. Learner performance does not improve over the long term. The final stage in the cycle is blame-finding with reasons ranging from not enough money, educator resistance, and educational systems resistant to change. The methods and reasoning for incorporating the technology are rarely addressed in the historical or market record. The reader of this series might recognize these statements already being made about immersive experiences. As such, hype cycles for immersive experiences are already underway.<br> </span></div>
<div style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-family: helvetica;">This last point deserves emphasis. Here are the steps again:</span></div>
<div style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-family: helvetica;"><br>1. Tech producers make the first "research".<br>2. Tech adopted, but learner performance does not improve long term.<br>3. Blame-finding ensues.</span></div>
<div style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-family: helvetica;"><br>I wanted to emphasize these points because they are going to appear in the research record that I will present. </span></div>
<h1 id="docs-internal-guid-195a7ea9-7fff-f06d-26c5-8b3e4fa397e0" style="line-height: 1.56; margin-bottom: 2pt; margin-top: 12pt; text-align: left;"></h1>
<h2 dir="ltr" style="line-height: 1.2; margin-bottom: 0pt; margin-top: 16pt;"><span style="background-color: transparent; color: #008575; font-size: 16pt; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: 400; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline;">Boom and bust cycles</span></h2>
<p><span style="font-family: helvetica;">Immersive experiences have already weathered several boom and bust cycles. One cycle began between 2003 and 2009. The desktop-based virtual reality program called Second Life, created by Linden Lab, attracted over 100 universities (Brown &amp; Sugar, 2009) and thousands of dollars of investment (Wecker, 2014).<br><br>In a sudden decision, Linden Lab eliminated its 50% discount for educational institutions (Harrison, 2010). What resulted was an educator exodus and fracture in the faith of immersive experiences for education. When referring to the <a href="https://www.chronicle.com/blogs/wiredcampus/woodbury-u-banned-from-second-life-again">shutdown of Woodbury University’s virtual campus</a> for breach of conduct, Jordan Bellino, a senior learner at the institution, described the hazard when one major company dominates use:<br><br>The incident suggests the dangers of online meeting spaces’ being run by companies, which get to decide who participates and who doesn’t. “It took years and thousands of dollars to make that virtual campus happen,” he said, “and it all vanished in a matter of an hour because Linden Lab pushed a button.” (Young, 2010, para. 12)<br><br>Major technology companies can single-handedly dictate use of immersive environments. This would be a valuable lesson lost before the next boom cycle began in 2018.</span></p>
<h2 dir="ltr" style="line-height: 1.2; margin-bottom: 0pt; margin-top: 16pt;"><span style="background-color: transparent; color: #008575; font-size: 16pt; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: 400; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline;">First course in virtual reality </span></h2>
<div style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-family: helvetica;"><br>After the launch of the consumer-oriented Quest headsets and the mandate for remote learning due to the COVID pandemic in 2020, interest in immersive environments surged. In June of 2021, Stanford opened their Virtual People course to 263 learners (Bailenson, 2021). </span></div>
<div style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-family: helvetica;"> </span></div>
<div><span style="font-family: helvetica;" data-keep-original-tag="false" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}"><a data-original-attrs="{&quot;data-original-href&quot;:&quot;https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEjG52c3NjJdyXUfLehb0TzRIsOhraeoRDEAZcWpPHnd06hsSnlWTTcWV4JO7zjrhjQWzZ5cqtRR3RdUjDgKbPPZnB6KGg1zNXz80XQGTtER4RBw8J104mqFdfhWWvj7g6HNdf-ECggRbao4XSCvLiFNZAdIQyqAzJQgIDwsa712H6lfLBDHEB_VQdCezn4/s1657/Stanford%20headline%201.png&quot;}" href="https://draft.blogger.com/#">
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEjG52c3NjJdyXUfLehb0TzRIsOhraeoRDEAZcWpPHnd06hsSnlWTTcWV4JO7zjrhjQWzZ5cqtRR3RdUjDgKbPPZnB6KGg1zNXz80XQGTtER4RBw8J104mqFdfhWWvj7g6HNdf-ECggRbao4XSCvLiFNZAdIQyqAzJQgIDwsa712H6lfLBDHEB_VQdCezn4/w400-h216/Stanford%20headline%201.png" border="0" data-is-external-image="true"><figcaption>Source: https://news.stanford.edu/stories/2021/11/new-class-among-first-taught-entirely-virtual-reality</figcaption></figure>
</a></span></div>
<div style="text-align: center;"> </div>
<div><span style="font-family: helvetica;" data-keep-original-tag="false" data-original-attrs="{&quot;style&quot;:&quot;&quot;}"><a data-original-attrs="{&quot;data-original-href&quot;:&quot;https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEivyPJt3dL6s8ty5FAUWuJULY45ZUFYW1vXevjPJnu63A5g2QMtXxntVbX2VvoixmP2semePWIpwSlQTxA5uVNfkOYmhUF4zo_v2sD5uXHyDa1fLh0OGP1ceOgdLEhxlry8q5WzO1MlSxAY_lwc8Z-uvxLjzDyhnPMCsPXffplckSBNwn4WXCElU0Rc9rU/s1877/Stanford%20headline%202.png&quot;}" href="https://draft.blogger.com/#">
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEivyPJt3dL6s8ty5FAUWuJULY45ZUFYW1vXevjPJnu63A5g2QMtXxntVbX2VvoixmP2semePWIpwSlQTxA5uVNfkOYmhUF4zo_v2sD5uXHyDa1fLh0OGP1ceOgdLEhxlry8q5WzO1MlSxAY_lwc8Z-uvxLjzDyhnPMCsPXffplckSBNwn4WXCElU0Rc9rU/w400-h224/Stanford%20headline%202.png" border="0" data-is-external-image="true"><figcaption>Source: https://www.scrippsnews.com/us-news/education/stanford-virtual-reality-class-puts-students-in-metaverse</figcaption></figure>
</a></span></div>
<div style="text-align: left;"> </div>
<div style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-family: helvetica;">The course was touted to be the first class in the world to be held inside of virtual reality (Hadhazy, 2021) which seemed to cast aside the nearly two-decade deep body of research on courses held as immersive experiences. The prestige of the course was further hyped when one of the course professors boasted:</span></div>
<div style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-family: helvetica;"><br></span>
<div style="margin-left: 40px; text-align: left;"><span style="font-family: helvetica;">I can now stand up in front of all my students and there's, you know, two hundred in the class, and I can say you will actually have a better chance of getting a job in the Valley because of taking this class because as of about a year ago, the most sought-after job in the Valley went from a data scientist to a VR engineer. (<a href="https://www.scrippsnews.com/us-news/education/stanford-virtual-reality-class-puts-students-in-metaverse">Bellini,</a> 2024, para 12)</span></div>
</div>
<div style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-family: helvetica;"><br>The VR-based learning resulted in greater presence, enjoyment, motivation, and transfer (Han &amp; Bailenson, 2024). However, within the course, all was not well. Video clips from the class showed learners struggling to control their avatars (Bailenson, 2021) and attending class just to stand around in circles (Bellini, 2021).</span></div>
<div>
<figure class="post__video"><iframe loading="lazy" width="560" height="314" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/gOLI_OIV3nc?si=jv2LF-d4Dz8sIZsf" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen"></iframe></figure>
</div>
<div style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-family: helvetica;"><br>In spite of the boasting, published reports illuminated problems with onboarding learners to the VR headset experience, unexpected software updates, and sudden platform shutdowns (Han &amp; Bailenson, 2024). </span></div>
<div style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-family: helvetica;"><br>The instructional design was described as <strong><i>learning by doing</i></strong>, but the syllabus showed a majority of outside-of-virtual-world writing and quiz items. Within the immersive environment, there were required weekly discussion sessions (Han et al., 2022) and one project where learners could import 3D (three-dimensional) objects to make a unique VR environment. My translation? That's not much doing, actually, as it relates to being a "virtual person". </span></div>
<div style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-family: helvetica;"> </span></div>
<div style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-family: helvetica;">Much to the professors’ astonishment, one group of learners made a mock fake moon landing production set (Brown et al., 2023). For the course instructors, this suddenly raised the specter that immersive experiences can create false depictions or fake memories, a topic that will be revisited in the ethical labyrinths section of this series.</span></div>
<p dir="ltr" style="line-height: 1.44; margin-bottom: 0pt; margin-top: 6pt;"><span style="font-family: helvetica;">In Part 3, I'll share another example of boom and bust from the immersive environments-for-education market.<br><br></span></p>
<h2 style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-family: helvetica;">Post-publication edit:</span></h2>
<p dir="ltr" style="line-height: 1.44; margin-bottom: 0pt; margin-top: 6pt;"><span style="font-family: helvetica;"><br>They say there is no editor like the "Publish" button and that makes me laugh because you DO spot errors after something has been published.  But in this case, it's not an error that I want to address, I want to add more depth and context to this post. Since it's my blog, I can. This work was previously planned to be a book chapter and as such, I held my tongue on some of my more pointed criticism and images. But here, I can lay out things more directly.<br></span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-family: helvetica;">Directly I am pointing to the </span>Communication 166/266:<span style="font-family: helvetica;">Virtual People course as a poor design from an instructional designer's point of view. I have studied the syllabus and read several articles and watched videos produced about the course.  You can read <a href="https://vhil.stanford.edu/downloads/comm166" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">the syllabus yourself!</a></span></p>
<p style="line-height: 1.44; margin-bottom: 0pt; margin-top: 6pt; text-align: left;"><span style="font-family: helvetica;"><br>What I can't find is how many credits the course was. Just guessing from the workload in the syllabus, I'd guess 2 credits.  Could be 3 but it also could be 1. I severely doubt it's 4. <br><br>Where do I get the platform to critique this course?<br><br>1. I have 14 years full time experience teaching online. Until ~2034, there are very few that can match me with that kind of full time online teaching experience. Bailenson's class was arguably not "online" by definition (it happened in June 2021 or so and that would be post-shutdown), but it appears to have happened entirely remotely with the exception of picking up the headsets. So I can claim some expertise about what SHOULD happen with digital-based, if not online, instruction.<br>2. My doctorate is in Instructional Design specifically *for Online Learning*. So I've spent my time focusing on that.<br>3. My research focus was and is learning in immersive environments (hence this article series).<br>4. Uniquely, <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/i-taught-one-earths-first-courses-oculus-quest-2-heather-dodds" target="_blank" rel="noopener">I ALSO taught a course using the Meta Quest 2s</a> which had a similar "survey" type of design. So what Bailenson did by visiting topics each week briefly is NOT part of my critique.<br><br>Three things are my main concerns here:</span></p>
<h4 style="line-height: 1.44; margin-bottom: 0pt; margin-top: 6pt; text-align: left;"><span style="font-family: helvetica;"><br><strong>1. Video clips show a ridiculous amount of on-boarding malarkey. </strong> </span></h4>
<p style="line-height: 1.44; margin-bottom: 0pt; margin-top: 6pt; text-align: left;"><span style="font-family: helvetica;">Said another way, bringing learners into a 3D environment, not acclimating them to this and then bringing in various models and just letting the users play is nice for an introduction. It does NOT make a course and certainly it does not argue for a widespread use of the technology.<br><br>I'm sure that in one version of the video, I could hear learners over and over again gathered in small groups supposedly "doing" something in VR only to hear "can anyone hear me?" as a COMMON statement. Take my word for it; a class filled <i>from beginning to end</i> with learners not being able to hear or be heard does not count for much learning.<br></span></p>
<p style="line-height: 1.44; margin-bottom: 0pt; margin-top: 6pt; text-align: left;"><span style="font-family: helvetica;">My point: there isn't evidence that anything other than some "visits" to VR happened.  And yet, over and over, this flagship course (my phrase) has learners that can't walk, can't wave, cannot follow instructions and (I guess) can't hear instructions. After week one, the learners *should* be on-boarded, all practiced up and ready to do harder things. 'Just walk over here for a group photo' should not feel like a nearly impossible task-- but the videos sure do make it look like it was.  <br><br>I had to giggle 😄 because in that "all class" photo, there is one avatar in 2D, not in a headset, because they don't have hands and their movement is all 2D-type, and they are the only one that looks "logical" in their behaviors.<br><br>2.<strong> Bailenson really shows his excitement  </strong></span><span style="font-family: helvetica;">(in the somewhat unprofessional video) <strong>but also the "un-put-togetherness" of this experience </strong>with the his statement: <br><br></span><span style="font-family: helvetica;">I can now stand up in front of all my students and there's, you know, two hundred in the class, and I can say you will actually have a better chance of getting a job in the Valley because of taking this class because as of about a year ago, the most sought-after job in the Valley went from a data scientist to a VR engineer. (<a href="https://www.scrippsnews.com/us-news/education/stanford-virtual-reality-class-puts-students-in-metaverse">Bellini,</a> 2024, para 12)</span><span style="font-family: helvetica;"><br></span></p>
<p dir="ltr" style="line-height: 1.44; margin-bottom: 0pt; margin-top: 6pt;"><span style="font-family: helvetica;"><br>I find it VERY hard to believe that this one course at the 100 and 200 level will lead to 200 new VR engineer's getting jobs in "the Valley".  Insert hard eyeroll here. 🙄  It looks extra bravado-y when he phrases it as "I can now stand up" as if he's really planning to do this or HAS done it.  It's a brag.  No humble about it.  Last I checked, the Valley wants to hire computer scientists, who should be in calculus class at the same time as this headset romp. Fact check: The Valley has been laying off VR teams.  So how's that 'better chance of getting a job' brag going for ya?<br><br>3. <strong>The learn-by-doing quote gets under my skin </strong>as an instructional designer. </span></p>
<p dir="ltr" style="line-height: 1.44; margin-bottom: 0pt; margin-top: 6pt;"><span style="font-family: helvetica;">Learn WHAT by doing WHAT, in this case? His students had to use pre-existing 3D models included in the ENGAGE platform (OK, fine-- but note that I didn't see ANY examples of models beyond ones we've already seen in ENGAGE advertising) to build a scene that was basically their final project. </span></p>
<p dir="ltr" style="line-height: 1.44; margin-bottom: 0pt; margin-top: 6pt;"><span style="font-family: helvetica;">(Again, disclosure: my students final project was a video mock-up of an immersive experience that they would design, if they could. The course taught no programming skills.) </span></p>
<p dir="ltr" style="line-height: 1.44; margin-bottom: 0pt; margin-top: 6pt;"><span style="font-family: helvetica;">So OK, it's fine that learners can't program after 1 course. Totally understood. But then the learners put together a final project scene that sounds like Bailenson's team spit out their coffee over...J. Brown source described the team experience as, "jarring" and wanted to coin a new phrase, "mis-experience."  What the phrase? Garbage in, garbage out?  You don't design a compelling course and the results surprise you?  Sigh.</span></p>
<p dir="ltr" style="line-height: 1.44; margin-bottom: 0pt; margin-top: 6pt;"><span style="font-family: helvetica;">It appears that they took the "made lemonade from lemons" approach. Note that I haven't mentioned ANYTHING about comparative learning outcomes related to this heralded course. Because there isn't any data on that. Not like there should be, but the research is remarkably silent 🤫 on that. <br><br>Also fact check on this: the Meta Quest 2 headsets are officially OUT of support and sale from Meta. So they are, as of this writing, outdated. I wonder how it's going over there at Stanford. Do they just ring up Mark and ask for 266 more headsets in the Meta Quest 3 type now?<br><br>I haven't mentioned, (actually I left it OUT), how much ENGAGE got free advertising from this mess. That's because they are really the main characters in the NEXT episode.<br><br></span></p>
<h1 id="docs-internal-guid-8b420ed1-7fff-d47f-93fa-e2c0f19b8607" dir="ltr" style="line-height: 1.56; margin-bottom: 2pt; margin-top: 12pt;"><span style="background-color: transparent; color: blue; font-size: 18pt; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: bold; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline;">References</span></h1>
<p><br>Bailenson, J. M. (2021). Stanford “Virtual People” class in the metaverse. [Video.] YouTube. <a href="https://youtu.be/gOLI_OIV3nc?si=if6DbOX43GESWTBd">https://youtu.be/gOLI_OIV3nc?si=if6DbOX43GESWTBd</a><br><br>Bellini, J. (2021, December 7). Stanford virtual reality class immerses students in metaverse. Scripps News. <a href="https://www.scrippsnews.com/us-news/education/stanford-virtual-reality-class-puts-students-in-metaverse">https://www.scrippsnews.com/us-news/education/stanford-virtual-reality-class-puts-students-in-metaverse</a><br><br>Brown, A., &amp; Sugar, W. (2010). Second life in education: The case of commercial online virtual reality applied to teaching and learning. Themes in Science and Technology education, 2(1-2), 107-115.<br><br>Brown, J., Bailenson, J., &amp; Hancock, J. (2023). Misinformation in virtual reality. Journal of Online Trust and Safety, 1(5).<br><br>Cuban, L. (2001). Oversold and underused: Computers in the classroom. Cambridge, MA: Harvard University.<br><br>Hadhazy, A. (2021, November 5). Stanford course allows students to learn about virtual reality while fully immersed in VR environments. Stanford Report. <a href="https://news.stanford.edu/stories/2021/11/new-class-among-first-taught-entirely-virtual-reality">https://news.stanford.edu/stories/2021/11/new-class-among-first-taught-entirely-virtual-reality</a><br><br>Han, E., &amp; Bailenson, J. N. (2024). Lessons for/in virtual classrooms: designing a model for classrooms inside virtual reality. Communication Education, 73(2), 234-243.<br><br>Harrison, D. (2010, November 3). Linden Lab to end Second Life educational discounts. THE Journal. https://thejournal.com/Articles/2010/11/03/Linden-Lab-To-End-Second-Life-Educational-Discounts.aspx?Page=1<br><br>Oppenheimer, T. (1997, July). The computer delusion. The Atlantic. <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/archive/1997/07/the-computer-delusion/376899/">https://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/archive/1997/07/the-computer-delusion/376899/</a><br><br>Wecker, M. (2014, April 22). What ever happened to Second Life? Chronicle Vitae. <a href="https://chroniclevitae.com/news/456-what-ever-happened-to-second-life">https://chroniclevitae.com/news/456-what-ever-happened-to-second-life</a>Young, J. (2010, April 21). Woodbury U. banned from Second Life, again. Chronicle of Higher Education. Wired Campus. <a href="https://www.chronicle.com/blogs/wiredcampus/woodbury-u-banned-from-second-life-again">https://www.chronicle.com/blogs/wiredcampus/woodbury-u-banned-from-second-life-again</a></p>
<hr>
<p>Did you miss the other parts of this series? Here they are!</p>
<p><strong><a href="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/part-1-from-myths-to-principles-navigating-instructional-design-in-immersive-environments.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Part 1: From Myths To Principles: Navigating Instructional Design in Immersive Environments</a></strong></p>
<p><strong><a href="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/part-2-the-immersive-environment-delusion.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Part 2: The Immersive Environment Delusion</a></strong></p>
<p><strong><a href="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/part-3-the-case-against-virtual-campuses.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Part 3: The Case Against Virtual Campuses</a></strong></p>
<p><strong><a href="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/part-4-myth-learners-learn-faster.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Part 4: Myth: Learners Learn Faster</a></strong></p>
<p><strong><a href="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/part-5-myth-learners-learn-more.html">Part 5: Myth: Learners Learn More<br><br></a><a href="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/part-6-myth-immersive-learning-is-active-learning.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Part 6: Myth: Immersive learning is active learning</a></strong></p>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Part 1 From Myths To Principles: Navigating Instructional Design in Immersive Environments</title>
        <author>
            <name>Heather Dodds</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/part-1-from-myths-to-principles-navigating-instructional-design-in-immersive-environments.html"/>
        <id>https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/part-1-from-myths-to-principles-navigating-instructional-design-in-immersive-environments.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/727/Part-1-From-Myths-To-Principles.png" medium="image" />
            <category term="XR"/>
            <category term="Research"/>
            <category term="Metaverse"/>

        <updated>2024-10-02T19:28:00-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/727/Part-1-From-Myths-To-Principles.png" alt="Decorative image with text: From Myths To Principles: Navigating Instructional Design in Immersive Environments with image of cloaked traveler on a mountian looking towards a break in gray clouds towards some buildings." />
                    This article begins a new series where I intend to continue to bust myths related to learning in immersive environments while also advocating for research-based decisions related to instructional design. Now if that sounded like gobbly-gook, this might not be the series for you. But,&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/727/Part-1-From-Myths-To-Principles.png" class="type:primaryImage" alt="Decorative image with text: From Myths To Principles: Navigating Instructional Design in Immersive Environments with image of cloaked traveler on a mountian looking towards a break in gray clouds towards some buildings." /></p>
                <div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"> </div>
<div style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-family: helvetica;">This article begins a new series where I intend to continue to bust myths related to learning in immersive environments while also advocating for research-based decisions related to instructional design.</span></div>
<div style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-family: helvetica;"><br>Now if that sounded like gobbly-gook, this might not be the series for you. But, for anyone with an interest in virtual worlds, the metaverse, or even a simple 2D simulation and the uses of these for education, this is the RIGHT place for you. <br></span></div>
<div style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-family: helvetica;"> </span></div>
<div style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-family: helvetica;">This is an updated version of my original 8-part Instructional Design in the Metaverse series. (Did you miss that? Here's my <a href="https://youtu.be/Rr4dzKLPlpQ" target="_blank" rel="noopener">3 minute explainer video</a>.) I estimate that I have at least 15 parts right now to start this series and new research comes in every day. However, t</span><span style="font-family: helvetica;">his being my blog, I intend to spill a little more tea here than I do in other places.</span><br><span style="font-family: helvetica;"><br>Buckle up buttercups</span>!<hr></div>
<h2 style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-family: helvetica;">Introduction</span></h2>
<p><span style="font-family: helvetica;"><br>A wondrous thing happens the first time a learner steps into the metaverse; the learner enters a land of digital imagination. The immersive technology creates and presents what the learner senses visually and auditorily. Because those experiences are digital creations, the possibilities can be as varied and broad as human imagination. This wide open promise of anything anywhere has attracted educators and researchers for more than two decades. Within the body of research generated from this attraction, significant challenges remain for those interested in the prudent application of the immersive learning design.<br><br>The global virtual reality (VR) industry is forecast to reach $435 billion in United States dollars within the next 6 years, reflecting a compounded annual growth rate of 27% (Yahoo Finance, 2023). Immersive or extended reality (XR) technologies are broad combinations of computer technology that overlays or fully surround the learner with digitally constructed sights, sounds, smell, taste, pressure, heat, and texture sensations (Ziker et al., 2021). XR as a broad term is understood to encompass virtual reality (VR), augmented reality (AR), and mixed reality (MR). Immersive experiences stand distinct as an educational media choice due to the factors of immersion, embodiment, and presence that arise within the learner (Southgate, 2020). This series will use the term immersive experiences to refer to the inclusive concept of learning within virtual reality, augmented reality, mixed reality, cross reality, transmedia, and the metaverse. <br><br>Immersive experiences are expected to expand within the next few years in the areas of education, industrial training, and healthcare where the influence of instructional design could be beneficial. Educators have already been turning to immersive experiences for uses such as simulation, training, providing access to limited resources and to bridge distances as a form of remote learning (Kavanaugh et al., 2017). New educators and designers, however, often express a sense of being overwhelmed at the idea of designing instruction that would essentially be spherical (as in, surrounding the learner) and containing infinite potential (immersive experiences could contain any information or process). Unquestioningly, everyone feels that the design work is complex. <br><br>Regardless, there are still educators who, despite sudden platform shutdowns and expensive contracts, feel that immersive experiences have 'enormous unrealized potential’ (Wecker, 2014). The complexity of designing for the metaverse calls for assistance from instructional design that focuses on “instructional methods, specific features that facilitate actual learning” (Honebein &amp; Reigeluth, 2023. p. 292). Unfortunately, heretofore immersive experiences have precipitated haphazard designs lacking guidance:<br><br></span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-family: helvetica;">Education researchers borrow heavily from the entertainment designers, who focus on engagement, and not necessarily on retention of content. The dearth of studies highlights the urgency for a set of guidelines for designing content that allows users to make appropriate choices in a spherical space. (Johnson-Glenberg, 2018, p. 7)</span></p>
<p> </p>
<div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"><a href="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEiKAnVqi0yw6m2-9oB2ReMYOZtH7O2fYJ3Dehzu58NrMi-_1psp2P4zJMVJ3bYBkJuz0eD3T9sUOPNziIB0DZowve02A7OaXM5ZkrjibkyASjZVcECkBfEaUfYUwW3ZjA-sFeztedBCLnfyuvitH_GklxLiEybTCngLuy-ffosdq8SOABVJEnuHWWvOxQU/s798/pasteurs+quadrant-911760832.jpg" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;">
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/727/pasteurs+quadrant-911760832.jpg" width="640" height="454" border="0" sizes="(max-width: 1920px) 100vw, 1920px" srcset="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/727/responsive/pasteurs+quadrant-911760832-xs.jpg 640w ,https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/727/responsive/pasteurs+quadrant-911760832-sm.jpg 768w ,https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/727/responsive/pasteurs+quadrant-911760832-md.jpg 1024w ,https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/727/responsive/pasteurs+quadrant-911760832-lg.jpg 1366w ,https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/727/responsive/pasteurs+quadrant-911760832-xl.jpg 1600w ,https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/727/responsive/pasteurs+quadrant-911760832-2xl.jpg 1920w"><figcaption><span style="font-family: helvetica;">Image source: https://publishingarchaeology.blogspot.com/2011/05/is-there-archaeology-in-pasteurs.html</span></figcaption></figure>
</a></div>
<p><span style="font-family: helvetica;">Therefore, this series will begin with looking at the current state of immersive experiences for learning research. Published research however, often falls short of the mark. This series will contribute to both fundamental and practical applications (Shi &amp; Evans, 2023), landing in Pasteur’s Quadrant as Mayer (2020) suggested, as “basic research in applied situations” (p. 22). This series draws from the body of published research in the form of a selective consumer; it discriminates seeking to understand the wise applications of immersive environments. Additionally, it addresses real problems faced by instructional designers and administrators. Staying grounded in reality will be very important as we journey into the research of virtual worlds. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-family: helvetica;">We will begin with some history, next post.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-family: helvetica;"> </span></p>
<hr>
<p>Did you miss the other parts of this series? Here they are!</p>
<p><strong><a href="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/part-1-from-myths-to-principles-navigating-instructional-design-in-immersive-environments.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Part 1: From Myths To Principles: Navigating Instructional Design in Immersive Environments</a></strong></p>
<p><strong><a href="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/part-2-the-immersive-environment-delusion.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Part 2: The Immersive Environment Delusion</a></strong></p>
<p><strong><a href="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/part-3-the-case-against-virtual-campuses.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Part 3: The Case Against Virtual Campuses</a></strong></p>
<p><strong><a href="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/part-4-myth-learners-learn-faster.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Part 4: Myth: Learners Learn Faster</a></strong></p>
<p><strong><a href="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/part-5-myth-learners-learn-more.html">Part 5: Myth: Learners Learn More<br><br></a><a href="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/part-6-myth-immersive-learning-is-active-learning.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Part 6: Myth: Immersive learning is active learning</a></strong></p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Instructional Design in the Metaverse Part 7 Design and Build</title>
        <author>
            <name>Heather Dodds</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/instructional-design-in-the-metaverse-part-7-design-and-build.html"/>
        <id>https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/instructional-design-in-the-metaverse-part-7-design-and-build.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/696/Part-7.png" medium="image" />
            <category term="Metaverse"/>

        <updated>2023-10-20T13:52:00-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/696/Part-7.png" alt="" />
                    At this point, we have all of the building blocks ready to begin a design. We know what works from 2D learning and what to try with 3D learning. Beginning the steps to launch an XR experience can feel more like a User Experience (UX)&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/696/Part-7.png" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <p> </p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">At this point, we have all of the building blocks ready to begin a design. We know what works from 2D learning and what to try with 3D learning. Beginning the steps to launch an XR experience can feel more like a User Experience (UX) project than an instructional design project, however. UX similarly uses storyboards, journey mapping, and personas which can be very helpful in designing emotion into the experience. Prototype versions can be ready for a few users to sample and give feedback. Overall, ID projects in the metaverse feel different because the designing and building phases <i>blend together</i> with test layouts requiring adjustment.</p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">Even at the final project launch, instructional designers (IDs) should observe how the learners are experiencing the design. IDs should be at the forefront with the learners, constantly evaluating what is working and what is not. It can be very helpful for IDs to observe what learners try first or how they explore the experience. In this way, design with this media is less of a one-way instance and more of an ongoing process. Remember <a class="article-editor-content__link article-editor-content__link" href="https://books.google.com/books?id=PXRJEAAAQBAJ&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;ots=UpbIsA4SJU&amp;dq=learning%20experience%20design%20Clark&amp;lr&amp;pg=PP1#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false" rel="noopener noreferrer">D. Clark's</a> 'always beginning, never ending' design advice? The following three sections represent lessons already learned in ID for XR designs.</p>
<h3 class="article-editor-content__heading">1 Focus on Purpose</h3>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">Determining purpose at the earliest stage is critical because the purpose guides many of the upcoming ID decisions. Traditional ID projects begin with these questions that ask about the main learning objective or goal.</p>
<ul class="article-editor-content__bullet-list">
<li class="article-editor-content__list-item">
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">"What will students be able to do at <strong>the end of the course</strong>" (<a class="article-editor-content__link article-editor-content__link" href="https://teachingcommons.stanford.edu/teaching-guides/foundations-course-design/theory-practice/teacher-centered-vs-student-centered" rel="noopener noreferrer">Stanford University</a>, 2023).</p>
</li>
<li class="article-editor-content__list-item">
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">“Focus on <strong>performance requirements</strong>” (Guy Wallace as quoted in <a class="article-editor-content__link article-editor-content__link" href="https://endurancelearning.com/blog/id-for-non-training-professionals/" rel="noopener noreferrer">Washburn</a>, 2023).</p>
</li>
<li class="article-editor-content__list-item">
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">“Identify desired <strong>results</strong>” (<a class="article-editor-content__link article-editor-content__link" href="https://tll.mit.edu/teaching-resources/course-design/backward-design/" rel="noopener noreferrer">MIT Teaching and Learning Lab</a>, 2023).</p>
</li>
<li class="article-editor-content__list-item">
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">“Think about what <strong>people are truly trying to do</strong> and realize that’s a system” (Don Norman as quoted in <a class="article-editor-content__link article-editor-content__link" href="https://blog.adobe.com/en/publish/2017/10/03/putting-people-first-tips-and-advice-from-ux-pioneer-don-norman" rel="noopener noreferrer">Faller</a>, 2017).</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">However, because the metaverse is an experience for the learners, it can be thought of as a place and time; it is like a field trip. </p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEhQdOoLUZQKa0Uh3shnPex7HElKkgD3agXf2yLpSc_-hB3cqx4nMhQbtJVzLQ9LmICQabtGUHXdCWYetPv5X_KT5z8J03J1qQwE4h23MCuw4xz7_YVN0e_xcXBNg2ZNk1hRSDZRrU31QA2VB2U5Elp9IpFya9tNnSdOEmCgzqg85wNq2O0Ic7CLkrL_wMg/w640-h428/Sistine%20Chapel%20(actual).jpg" alt="Photo interior of the Sistine Chapel with painted walls and ceiling." width="640" height="428" border="0" data-original-height="1555" data-original-width="2323" data-is-external-image="true"><figcaption>Sistine Chapel (actual)</figcaption></figure>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">Here is an example: An art history instructor wants to recreate a visit to the Sistine Chapel. Rather than first creating an XR building or finding an XR recreated chapel, the ID can determine what is the most important experience for the learner. It could be:</p>
<ul class="article-editor-content__bullet-list">
<li class="article-editor-content__list-item">
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">Appreciating Michelangelo’s artistic style</p>
</li>
<li class="article-editor-content__list-item">
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">Imagining how the artist would have painted in the space</p>
</li>
<li class="article-editor-content__list-item">
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">Discussing the role of sponsors for art</p>
</li>
<li class="article-editor-content__list-item">
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">Viewing the artwork like real life (looking up)</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">Each of those different purposes could generate a different learning design.</p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">Let’s say the instructor wants to emphasize<strong> viewing the artwork within the chapel, on the curved ceiling and the soaring upper walls and how this viewing angle intersects with perspective</strong>. Noting prior experiences, learners might have only seen this art <i>somewhat</i> straight-on from photographs. </p>
<p> </p>
<div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"><a href="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEg-K1xbwtU9xkxvlHuKtVfGHeQTU8UedVJ0rAA0KSaNbsCfcXcGPBApL8vAFXV1cCYWKIi7w4sWcJOo4QmF0vu69bf67UaBsl9uazUlQhwzglbBjIJO5Lx9E50JpYJ90AzyUqpFmB72oTax0SpSstZ5L858kefPtHwfY5E_aZY-RrLHUGcdJ2kUUiSEOAE/s1793/Michelangelo_-_Sistine_Chapel_ceiling_-_bay_7.jpg" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;">
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/696/Michelangelo_-_Sistine_Chapel_ceiling_-_bay_7.jpg" alt="Photo of the Noah ceiling bay at the Sistine Chapel. Viewing straight up into a ceiling bay. Note that from this view, both left and right are looking down, even when you are looking up." width="640" height="178" border="0" sizes="(max-width: 1920px) 100vw, 1920px" srcset="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/696/responsive/Michelangelo_-_Sistine_Chapel_ceiling_-_bay_7-xs.jpg 640w ,https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/696/responsive/Michelangelo_-_Sistine_Chapel_ceiling_-_bay_7-sm.jpg 768w ,https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/696/responsive/Michelangelo_-_Sistine_Chapel_ceiling_-_bay_7-md.jpg 1024w ,https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/696/responsive/Michelangelo_-_Sistine_Chapel_ceiling_-_bay_7-lg.jpg 1366w ,https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/696/responsive/Michelangelo_-_Sistine_Chapel_ceiling_-_bay_7-xl.jpg 1600w ,https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/696/responsive/Michelangelo_-_Sistine_Chapel_ceiling_-_bay_7-2xl.jpg 1920w"><figcaption>Viewing straight up into a ceiling bay. Note now from this view, both left and right are looking down, even when you are looking up. Michelangelo?! Escher much?</figcaption></figure>
</a></div>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">In real life, the art appears above the viewer. Thus, there are two different points to view from: in photographs, the view is from what would be mid-air. In real life, the view is from the ground. </p>
<p> </p>
<div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"><a href="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEgQI-bR3pi023lvvxv0tctbjVDr4pTAkIQkZvt7rxb0vPkPxSkNn-mXR94Zp_2EQSxF_gsjoFB1YsUgIrChiB-cj0JjpMp1wpztf4u1NnGOWy3rKQ-U_yDeS3QLE6xXoWOw3RoCg0XvZwo_gibHXvLHBV71yike7Y3HjTjLL8oQUM3ow2vtkMQ5zZn9tak/s1024/Sistine_Chapel_ceiling_(3395223825)_editted.png" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;">
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/696/Sistine_Chapel_ceiling_(3395223825)_editted.png" alt="The Noah bay in context of the full ceiling where the shadow effect of a left and right curving side now make more visual sense above the chapel walls." width="486" height="640" border="0" sizes="(max-width: 1920px) 100vw, 1920px" srcset="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/696/responsive/Sistine_Chapel_ceiling_(3395223825)_editted-xs.png 640w ,https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/696/responsive/Sistine_Chapel_ceiling_(3395223825)_editted-sm.png 768w ,https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/696/responsive/Sistine_Chapel_ceiling_(3395223825)_editted-md.png 1024w ,https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/696/responsive/Sistine_Chapel_ceiling_(3395223825)_editted-lg.png 1366w ,https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/696/responsive/Sistine_Chapel_ceiling_(3395223825)_editted-xl.png 1600w ,https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/696/responsive/Sistine_Chapel_ceiling_(3395223825)_editted-2xl.png 1920w"><figcaption>Same ceiling bay, showing how the side pieces appear to "curve down" to vertical walls, creating a left/right sides illusion. So...WHAT is the PURPOSE you want to teach?</figcaption></figure>
</a></div>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">In XR, designers could use either or both. The learners might be able to first view the artwork from the floor and then <strong>fly</strong> and compare looking at the art from mid-air. In this way, the learners will have comparative viewing from different angles…something that the real life Chapel can not easily provide. This satisfies the instructor's request to focus on the viewing experience by providing a standard replication and then a different angle as comparison. </p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEjT-SK3eX6qkUOBEd98qNugyWbe2PcbwHTpkXmOg01IzBUR5ZN7czDrDNaeUzU9hxJiOgPDxSRNypt2-0XrE_ysSliZfIwtazZ0BXsG-JUmqT_ly1Bh_OxnIJOaHee-hSsGCw_1qvCskvxRE8EI3W-NmE1mlR_WGAasYE03QEK5DAYFw8NzXT5XwQp8kXc/w640-h360/Title%20Page(1).png" alt="Side by side photo comparison of the real Sistine Chapel and a virtual Sistine Chapel. Except for some light, nearly indistinguishable from each other." width="640" height="360" border="0" data-original-height="1080" data-original-width="1920" data-is-external-image="true"><figcaption>Side by side photo comparison of the real Sistine Chapel and a virtual Sistine Chapel. Except for some light, nearly indistinguishable from each other. </figcaption></figure>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEhPm_KiPFstWWt45wlhJ4JW-8ndGFXrsZSTTBVvew9HzGeZL778w6ws0FgySrKJaqxim53cW9S-aIj6no66FWgzLBtN4aIXtau6gUnE5MYHZmPPORkmS2zwrtq32mNxFYxHePalGDEDx7T2rW6h5naNmnSCz-nXMfFBcD2kMqM17sq_TArrEIsBTrc60Nc/w640-h360/Sistine%20Chapel%20for%20sale.png" alt="A virtual Sistine Chapel is for sale at Sketchfab" width="640" height="360" border="0" data-original-height="748" data-original-width="1327" data-is-external-image="true"><figcaption>Sistine Chapel - virtual is for sale for $39 US at Sketchfab</figcaption></figure>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">By thinking about the learner’s experience, the designer can start to list which aspects of the real world need to be replicated (e.g., gravity, enclosed space) and which aspects will not be from reality (e.g. flying on demand). In summary, <strong>this adage fits: begin with the end in mind.</strong></p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">For XR designs, ask “what is the feeling that you want your learner to have?” That might come as a surprise– elevating feeling as a primary design priority. The next section will address why the feel of an XR design is more important than its content.</p>
<h3 class="article-editor-content__heading">2 Emotion Transcends Language</h3>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">Pixar is a highly successful <a class="article-editor-content__link article-editor-content__link" href="https://www.nyfa.edu/student-resources/pixars-rules-for-great-storytelling/" rel="noopener noreferrer">storytelling</a> company. In the Pixar narrative model, the highest production emphasis is placed on the emotions within the story (<a class="article-editor-content__link article-editor-content__link" href="https://youtu.be/1rMnzNZkIX0" rel="noopener noreferrer">Khan Academy Labs</a>, 2017). Characters and setting are considered secondarily. </p>
<p> </p>
<div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"><a href="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEhTYzaFGXc9pBOvMegjCPpSgdG9U2ySyenApxFScQzNsCaTT9dyHuuCrc8t6HPdXv8jIITJLusbJpFQd9jAp56WFBvrpwj0xdR2W3zzgutS6i8zj06hVK7AwUT79ul0-2LJBDuNsjwyRVR-h1iKxpid5AHQJ75hekENtRghJPtjD0mEIVZauJWEo4nkDZU/s818/The_Incredibles_-_colorscript-796068816.png" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;">
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/696/The_Incredibles_-_colorscript-796068816.png" alt="Lou Romano created wordless, colored storyboards for The Incredibles based on a 1960s esthetic. It worked" width="640" height="640" border="0" sizes="(max-width: 1920px) 100vw, 1920px" srcset="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/696/responsive/The_Incredibles_-_colorscript-796068816-xs.png 640w ,https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/696/responsive/The_Incredibles_-_colorscript-796068816-sm.png 768w ,https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/696/responsive/The_Incredibles_-_colorscript-796068816-md.png 1024w ,https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/696/responsive/The_Incredibles_-_colorscript-796068816-lg.png 1366w ,https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/696/responsive/The_Incredibles_-_colorscript-796068816-xl.png 1600w ,https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/696/responsive/The_Incredibles_-_colorscript-796068816-2xl.png 1920w"><figcaption>Lou Romano created <strong>wordless</strong>, colored storyboards for The Incredibles based on a 1960s esthetic. It worked. Everyone else could build from these emotion-evoking images.</figcaption></figure>
</a></div>
<blockquote class="article-editor-content__blockquote">
<blockquote><strong>Emotional coinage works in XR storytelling because emotion transcends language;</strong> it does not need a text pop-up or an AI translator.</blockquote>
</blockquote>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">When an emotion can be relayed in some sort of visual or sound media, the designer can worry less about language translation or exactness in the metaverse. XR works naturally in this realm. Combining emotion with narrative plot creates designs where the learner is truly at the center because the learner becomes the lead character in the story. They are pulled along the learning journey because their character (their avatar) is experiencing the story. </p>
<p> </p>
<div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"><a href="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEi-PuFhQcjWYOvBUiG62dENiImnIt24D6cR5OvcsgEob2w4avvB5GFJZn1P_y1yl81WqgxhmOuqj12-eS6qWJuQjVyIhnORfTuWv62mWp0ymY7pA9OhWX7TvovorPouaniFKexriZJ1PfVsrAS9lQtLb1_epEQtn08wixg4qDvWpjQ0PtLy4d0g6daA6uw/s474/th-2487672165.jpeg" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;">
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/696/th-2487672165.jpeg" alt="Disney advertising graphic from Secrets of the Empire, Star Wars. A robot gestures to children to help in the fight against Star Troopers." width="640" height="360" border="0" sizes="(max-width: 1920px) 100vw, 1920px" srcset="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/696/responsive/th-2487672165-xs.jpeg 640w ,https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/696/responsive/th-2487672165-sm.jpeg 768w ,https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/696/responsive/th-2487672165-md.jpeg 1024w ,https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/696/responsive/th-2487672165-lg.jpeg 1366w ,https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/696/responsive/th-2487672165-xl.jpeg 1600w ,https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/696/responsive/th-2487672165-2xl.jpeg 1920w"><figcaption>Credit: Disney. Concept art showing 3 great things: 1 A clear "invite" to join the story 2 Headsets and non-headset users portrayed simultaneously. 3 Girls clearly invited, who are, apparently, good shots.</figcaption></figure>
</a></div>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph"><a class="article-editor-content__link article-editor-content__link" href="https://youtu.be/4o__z7aPlMw?si=PvpIGHdsJdL-IVs2&amp;t=198" rel="noopener noreferrer">Alger</a> illustrated these atomic design elements used to relay emotion: line, color, motion, lighting, spatial arrangement, sound timbre, haptic sensations, user proprioception, or visual elements like iridescence and specularity (2020). </p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEgrv9QGdxfuRvmtDB1KQQXn1VRcqzADt0RbkXfM3vDJCf46UWmHwFApYY6yFs2Th9IcVhpXtDnfxN4_dV9O1vPzdFNMp0qeq8dbzbkcVT3EdvUbQQ9gr_9b1yZg5utfS8_mX8qdWUUJrdPgW7XvTjp7SFdfuS8zUDrbl6gasJ_dFECRCW4ErLsPN_w2dQo/w640-h360/Title%20Page.png" alt="Four panel graphic with text: How design creates feeling with examples from line, color, movement, and form/shape. Credit: Alger 2020." width="640" height="360" border="0" data-original-height="1080" data-original-width="1920" data-is-external-image="true"><figcaption>Alger, 2020. </figcaption></figure>
<div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"> </div>
<div class="article-editor-content__iframe-embed">Just the basics of <strong>visual</strong> design, there is so much more for XR including sound design, body movement and placement, temperature and pressure, and smell!</div>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">IDs might want to work with designers from industrial or interior design, architects, or public space planners. [Hot tip: want to read more? The Internet Library has <a class="article-editor-content__link article-editor-content__link" href="https://archive.org/details/the-pocket-universal-principles-of-design-150-essential-tools" rel="noopener noreferrer">The Pocket Universal Principles Of Design 150 Essential Tools</a>.</p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEilWvgewhZCCDKrVUz6Gx1AKo_akwdESdwPnK1u38hAJy11zOegTVha1ycSxgv8YeAeZaNGrlKZAocNfuiMGK2VXank0f9tvatOkrrCC2ah5r0xrR1lNHoWNI0FV8-9hgeH6f5XhsLGN2ufT-mIahA3UwqDp2LSzxPPiO5UdbfHUp36pdCL4ORUpKvKilc/w640-h444/Principles%20of%20design%20book.png" alt="Capture from inside  The Pocket Universal Principles Of Design 150 Essential Tools with diagram showing that high ceilings evoke creativity and low ceilings foster focus." width="640" height="444" border="0" data-original-height="993" data-original-width="1430" data-is-external-image="true"><figcaption>I like this page particularly linking ceiling height with "feeling" in spaces, proposing the high ceilings spur creativity whereas low ceilings foster focus.</figcaption></figure>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">In planning a design, IDs can ask the instructor what the main emotion is that they want their learners to feel within the space (curiosity, happiness, fear, proficiency, etc.).</p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">The emotions can, of course, change as the story changes. In prototypes, IDs should ask learners what feelings they have in the XR space. Does the feeling match the purpose/goal? If not, the design needs to be changed to foster the emotion that is intended.</p>
<h3 class="article-editor-content__heading">3 Real World Correlation</h3>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">After the purpose is established and the central emotions are noted for a learning experience, the ID can determine how much of a real world correlation there is to the XR experience.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>For instance, when coming up against a design challenge in XR, IDs should ask, “How is this done in the real world?”</p>
</blockquote>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">The answer might be that the learner does a behavior (e.g. takes notes or alters a piece of equipment) or retrieves more information (e.g. looks at a reference source). With some consideration, the real world solution can be strategized together with the Multimedia Principles and created in XR. For example, if learners are struggling to remember a series of steps, do they need a nearby poster as a visual aid? If learners are getting something wrong with timing, do they need a stopwatch or clock? In XR, posters and clocks do not need to necessarily <i>hang on walls</i>. </p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEi22vDEFrTPHixDsS5V2xQlYId8EbhlZ5hbNTeroaxQCL2ACVHs0MZgniZ4Go9csTPnnCda-aSF24a0E-W9vt0Gxij68JM2iN_JTnt9x8_kQcyw2iFGlxGZewbCH9IL0rvPbq4Cy0ZvzmRTmjzTzzErj8Rt7WolpjC5_3uc2E5BVgLvJAf4bak-L-Lius4/w400-h206/Screenshot%202023-10-17%20124529.png" alt="Timer appears in the upper left corner, but it could be placed anywhere, or appear on demand." width="400" height="206" border="0" data-original-height="749" data-original-width="1454" data-is-external-image="true"><figcaption>Capture from a rabbit counting experience. The timer appears in the upper left corner indicating 33 seconds left. Timers and clocks can be placed anywhere in XR. </figcaption></figure>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">Combining what we already know from the Multimedia Principles will maximize the opportunity to learn <strong>by placing the relevant information when and where the learner will need it.</strong></p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">Starting with real world correlations is the healthy first step, but next, the IDs should consider <strong>what affordances</strong> XR can further provide. For example, do the learners need to fly or go inside an object? XR easily provides the ability to go through what would be solid objects like walls. Referring to a prior example, if a learner needs access to a clock, can a floating one be put into the learner's field of view, but not necessarily on a wall or wrist? By imagining the experience in pieces or segments, an ID can deconstruct what is necessary to drive the experience along and then rebuild those segments with the added possibilities of 3D design.</p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">Here is another example: an experience is replicating a spacewalk in outer space. The learning objective is to have the learner follow the correct procedure despite stressful conditions. The learner needs to put on a space suit following the correct procedure and check it for safety before leaving the spaceship. The emotional tone is to be calm and methodical even if the situation is urgent. What is the real world correlation to this experience? It might be donning protective equipment at a cold weather research station. This is a cognitively correlated event; the thought process is very similar. Thus, we can use this real world event to drive the design of the XR event. Items need to be put on in a certain order and checked for safety before going outside. </p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEjvt9JlQwiqcho6h3WDMbjYvHX6DhO9RAkJU51CAfw0FUFid1Nx6__Wy8mScv807osQNHpQdETh7LwJ1KQBetjzJRQLl4YOncIJqsVMpXlblwC6PbwT9lncp0nsred-Keo-q6wTVathUDMETGUvvh5GIA4gRGwGzylDG8UJbYaLM-bk1ToC-SijFepAX6U/w640-h360/Analogous%20experiences.png" alt="Graphic with text: Analogous experiences showing that protective clothing for astronauts and Antarctic visitors are similar. Therefore, we could use the latter to help build XR instructions for the former." width="640" height="360" border="0" data-original-height="1080" data-original-width="1920" data-is-external-image="true"><figcaption>Bundle up, baby, it's cold outside.</figcaption></figure>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">The XR design might want to include an alarm sound or flashing light to create urgency. Some sort of ‘buddy check’ system might stand by so that after the learner puts on the equipment, it is checked by another entity. Including alarms and safety checks are correlations to real world elements that can be built into the experience<i>.</i> The details of surrounding walls and floors or what is happening outside the spaceship do not influence this learning event. <a class="article-editor-content__link article-editor-content__link" href="https://www.cambridge.org/highereducation/books/multimedia-learning/FB7E79A165D24D47CEACEB4D2C426ECD#overview" rel="noopener noreferrer">Mayer</a> (2020) refers to these as <strong>seductive details</strong> – interesting, but they detract from the learning. Therefore, those details can be minimized in the surrounding design.</p>
<hr class="article-editor-content__horizontal-rule">
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">Part 8 is the last part!! It will acknowledge the limitations of what we know from research so far. But I've tucked one of my best tips into Part 8 before I conclude. Stay tuned, fellow babies*, for one last time.</p>
<figure class="post__image" ><img loading="lazy" src="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/696/ID-in-the-Meta-Part-7.png" alt="" width="2240" height="1260" sizes="(max-width: 1920px) 100vw, 1920px" srcset="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/696/responsive/ID-in-the-Meta-Part-7-xs.png 640w ,https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/696/responsive/ID-in-the-Meta-Part-7-sm.png 768w ,https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/696/responsive/ID-in-the-Meta-Part-7-md.png 1024w ,https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/696/responsive/ID-in-the-Meta-Part-7-lg.png 1366w ,https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/696/responsive/ID-in-the-Meta-Part-7-xl.png 1600w ,https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/696/responsive/ID-in-the-Meta-Part-7-2xl.png 1920w">
<figcaption >Decorative image: Prompt: Wide angle shot from the side, in the style of full color charcoal and Legend of Zelda game cover art, a female profile in a hooded cloak climbing up a mountain towards light, she carries a flame in one hand, in the style of deep indigo, light silver, enchanting lighting, blue and green color scheme --ar 16:9 </figcaption>
</figure>
<hr class="article-editor-content__horizontal-rule">
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph"><a class="article-editor-content__link article-editor-content__link" href="https://heatheredodds.blogspot.com/2023/10/instructional-design-in-metaverse-part-1.html" rel="noopener noreferrer">Part 1</a> was the Introduction.</p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph"><a class="article-editor-content__link article-editor-content__link" href="https://heatheredodds.blogspot.com/2023/10/instructional-design-in-metaverse-part-2.html" rel="noopener noreferrer">Part 2</a> covered Theory and Scope.</p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph"><a class="article-editor-content__link article-editor-content__link" href="https://heatheredodds.blogspot.com/2023/10/instructional-design-in-metaverse-part.html" rel="noopener noreferrer">Part 3</a> was Myths versus Reality.</p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph"><a class="article-editor-content__link article-editor-content__link" href="https://heatheredodds.blogspot.com/2023/10/instructional-design-in-metaverse-part_8.html" rel="noopener noreferrer">Part 4</a> covered the Characteristics of Success.</p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph"><a class="article-editor-content__link article-editor-content__link" href="https://heatheredodds.blogspot.com/2023/10/instructional-design-in-metaverse-part_10.html" rel="noopener noreferrer">Part 5</a> was What is the same between 2D and 3D design?</p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph"><a href="https://heatheredodds.blogspot.com/2023/10/instructional-design-in-metaverse-part_02074647801.html">Part 6 </a>was What is different between 2D and 3D design?</p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">Want to see my full references? <a class="article-editor-content__link article-editor-content__link" href="https://heatheredodds.blogspot.com/2023/10/instructional-design-in-metaverse.html" rel="noopener noreferrer">Have at it</a>.</p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">*Apologies if you don't catch the reference to <a class="article-editor-content__link article-editor-content__link" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dr._Johnny_Fever" rel="noopener noreferrer">Johnny Fever from WKRP</a> where groups of people were "fellow babies".</p>
<hr>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">##InstructionalDesign #XR #Multimedia #Principles #Mayer #LXD #ID #InstructionalDesigner #WebXR #3D #2D #Approach #LearnerCentric #NarrativePlot #Storytelling #Purpose #Design #Emotion #PrinciplesOfDesign #RealWorld #Correlation #edtech #DonNorman #GuyWallace</p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph"> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Instructional Design in the Metaverse Part 6 What is Different?</title>
        <author>
            <name>Heather Dodds</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/instructional-design-in-the-metaverse-part-6-what-is-different.html"/>
        <id>https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/instructional-design-in-the-metaverse-part-6-what-is-different.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/697/Part-6-What-is-Different.png" medium="image" />
            <category term="XR"/>
            <category term="Metaverse"/>

        <updated>2023-10-15T14:30:00-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/697/Part-6-What-is-Different.png" alt="Decorative image with text: Instructional Design in the Metaverse. Our metaverse explorer leaves the laboratory with the secrets to design and she heads out into the dark world." />
                    Welcome to Part 6! Are you alive? By my calculation, when this goes live, 3 intrepid souls have read all of Parts 1-5 before this. (Insert laughter with tears 😅). Indeed, you may have found this in isolation of the other parts! That's OK, I'm&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/697/Part-6-What-is-Different.png" class="type:primaryImage" alt="Decorative image with text: Instructional Design in the Metaverse. Our metaverse explorer leaves the laboratory with the secrets to design and she heads out into the dark world." /></p>
                <div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"> </div>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">Welcome to Part 6! Are you alive? By my calculation, when this goes live, 3 intrepid souls have read all of Parts 1-5 before this. (Insert laughter with tears 😅). Indeed, you may have found this in isolation of the other parts! That's OK, I'm cool with modularization. Feel free to "go around the Horn" at some other point in the future and read Parts 1-5 later.</p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">Oh! And, for those 3 travelers AND everyone else, I am making an explainer video of all of this content. But it comes with 2 caveats:</p>
<ol class="article-editor-content__ordered-list">
<li class="article-editor-content__list-item">
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">No references or quotes. Just ideas.</p>
</li>
<li class="article-editor-content__list-item">
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">Because it moves with a preset piece of music, each idea will have a limited amount of screen time: 2.4 seconds, to be precise.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">Finally, I'll probably write a full BTS (Behind The Scenes) on this article series. For those of you that love BTS content, that one will be for you. Translation: these articles were NOT written to be sound-bite worthy.  What I write in the BTS will be.</p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">This is basically the second of two parts that were originally together: Part 5 is what is the SAME about designing between 2D and 3D and this is what is different.</p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">Long story short?</p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">Here is where the fun begins.</p>
<div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"><a href="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEjqbKIipta0O-oUgy9seGBDzNBEe4PGDGJkr8ICfhyuyjr-3bCEr4pAlwZDWkcqXPN4CZwoFRRmENtP3fRF90DRv7I1TEPi2VlF18eZMD6JdZvXye0pjatz45akoW4vW2Iro4M1bZ135ap1Gtu8zFYrt_WKOwFjEPQe_-FtL7EyvSTYM1N9cZk0m_c5bjE/s498/fun-this-is-where-the-fun-begins-3562248195.gif" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img loading="lazy" src="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/697/fun-this-is-where-the-fun-begins-3562248195.gif" alt="Gif of Anakin Skywalker saying This is where the fun begins." width="320" height="254" border="0"></a></div>
<h2 class="article-editor-content__heading">2D to 3D: What Is Different</h2>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">A learner could learn from a book how to enter a store and buy something. A learner could also learn from entering a real store and buying something. Both are ways to complete the learning, but the designs– that is, how to structure the learning from start to finish, will be different. The book is analogous to direct instruction. There are times when direct instruction will be the better approach. The real store is analogous to experiential learning. There are times when experiential learning will be the better approach. The approaches are different; there is no inherently better approach for all situations.  </p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">These elements in this section are not meant to imply that they exclusively belong to XR media. That is, many other forms of media contain these same elements. These items are listed here because they are often found within and indeed<i> are combined</i> in design solutions in XR.</p>
<h3 class="article-editor-content__heading">1 Narrative Plot</h3>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph"><a class="article-editor-content__link article-editor-content__link" href="https://books.google.com/books?id=v1uzCgAAQBAJ&amp;lpg=PR17&amp;ots=TNCJkGdMdm&amp;dq=clark%20mayer&amp;lr&amp;pg=PR17#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false" rel="noopener noreferrer">Clark and Mayer</a> observed that humans are sense makers and attempt to derive meaning from life experiences (2016). Learners engage in making meaningful connections when words and pictures align during experiences. Meaning is also deeply embedded in the storytelling approach, where it is often the journey that the protagonist goes through that remains memorable long after a story has ended. <a class="article-editor-content__link article-editor-content__link" href="https://books.google.com/books?id=PXRJEAAAQBAJ&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;ots=UpbIsA4SJU&amp;dq=learning%20experience%20design%20Clark&amp;lr&amp;pg=PP1#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false" rel="noopener noreferrer">D. Clark</a> argued, “learning experiences are exactly that, experiences designed to change us, specifically our long term memories” (2022, p. 7). Further, D. Clark advocated for a balanced use of storytelling, explaining that it can bring life to dry information, but should not be overused and wander into a “Disneyfication of learning as entertainment” (2022, p. 7). Lastly, D. Clark argued that stories for learning should be designed as “always beginnings, never ends-in-themselves” if the learning is to be applicable beyond the experience, into the “long tail of practice, transfer, and performance” (2022, p. 7).</p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">Points for poetry, D. Clark! </p>
<blockquote> “always beginnings, never ends-in-themselves”</blockquote>
<p> </p>
<div class="separator align-left" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"><a href="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEjX6PaSD29tfvnr7BdTm3VugUb83udyPwOOxQ6W2TCyNPiWiMsv1NPTY9lKWIjfVkY_BXmh9dIo_8yznVXj55ak8b03rgE3RFXVtHjZL1506Z_s_6wZ21F40SqqFz8Jg62jYQ5R8EIGLHKYCc2UJJNw4KYdFMEQ9dfz4BF_20mnaitls-z-HU_pCY8a3Ds/s1456/heather_dodds_in_cinematic_style_enchantment_a_storyteller_with_d90ac9bf-70a7-47b4-9d52-d352d93d975b.png" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;">
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/697/heather_dodds_in_cinematic_style_enchantment_a_storyteller_with_d90ac9bf-70a7-47b4-9d52-d352d93d975b.png" alt="Decorative Image: Our metaverse explorer is exchanging stories with other storytellers." width="640" height="358" border="0" sizes="(max-width: 1920px) 100vw, 1920px" srcset="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/697/responsive/heather_dodds_in_cinematic_style_enchantment_a_storyteller_with_d90ac9bf-70a7-47b4-9d52-d352d93d975b-xs.png 640w ,https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/697/responsive/heather_dodds_in_cinematic_style_enchantment_a_storyteller_with_d90ac9bf-70a7-47b4-9d52-d352d93d975b-sm.png 768w ,https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/697/responsive/heather_dodds_in_cinematic_style_enchantment_a_storyteller_with_d90ac9bf-70a7-47b4-9d52-d352d93d975b-md.png 1024w ,https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/697/responsive/heather_dodds_in_cinematic_style_enchantment_a_storyteller_with_d90ac9bf-70a7-47b4-9d52-d352d93d975b-lg.png 1366w ,https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/697/responsive/heather_dodds_in_cinematic_style_enchantment_a_storyteller_with_d90ac9bf-70a7-47b4-9d52-d352d93d975b-xl.png 1600w ,https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/697/responsive/heather_dodds_in_cinematic_style_enchantment_a_storyteller_with_d90ac9bf-70a7-47b4-9d52-d352d93d975b-2xl.png 1920w"><figcaption>Humans crave stories that bring meaning </figcaption></figure>
</a></div>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">Indeed, the storytelling approach in learning pulls the learner through the experience. To use storytelling, the learner should experience a flow through their experience, a beginning and middle of the story. The end could happen in XR or more substantially outside of XR into desired application. The learning experience <strong>should be planned and not haphazard.</strong> Learners should be guided on a planned route. XR storytelling can be first person or group experiences. Regardless, each learner is a protagonist; their decisions determine what they will experience. Recalling the constructivist learning theory foundation, what the learners <i>experience</i> becomes the learning experience that is being designed <i>for</i>. If learners are exposed to situations where they actively construct their knowledge, then the reality that the learners construct was constructed <i>by them</i>, not constructed by the media or by others. Further, learners do not arrive as empty vessels to be passively filled with information if they are the protagonists of their own learning event. Learners add, sort, emphasize, or suppress new experiences when compared to old experiences.  Subsequently, a learner already experienced in real life (non-XR) is bringing those experiences into XR with them. In summary, <strong>learners arrive already ready to experience a story. Thus, narrative plot or a story arc is a good approach to XR instructional design.</strong></p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">Plot, narrative, or narrative plot are all descriptions of phases within storytelling. There are slight variances in names but the phases generally focus on the user’s (or in our case, the learner’s) experience (<a class="article-editor-content__link article-editor-content__link" href="https://books.google.com/books?id=DHo3DwAAQBAJ&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;ots=mZnAwii8NJ&amp;dq=Lichaw%2C%20D.%20(2016).%20The%20user's%20journey%3A%20Storymapping%20projects%20that%20people%20love.%20New%20York%3A%20Rosenfeld%20Media&amp;lr&amp;pg=PP1#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false" rel="noopener noreferrer">Lichaw</a>, 2016). </p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEib7_Z17dgwlIEih2h-Rhv3XOX7XYZ_Moopn1pT_lo1hyHKkrhZ3QqDXcJH4mdCn-JyrG8vVZi31NSozmigpSIt9n_9XNR1lnZeq_LA6h3oHImQJGt_Hvqx9ZnR17C1KH4JHOb_YTvLV_0qkDMYJjQ1FBvLJlagV5n2jJd_jt6rqcROf_54OQqBeoE_uVA/w640-h406/Narrative%20plot%20Lichaw.png" alt="Narrative Plot steps from Lichaw: Exposition, Inciting incident,  Rising action, Crisis, Climax, Denoument, End." width="640" height="406" border="0" data-original-height="886" data-original-width="1400" data-is-external-image="true"><figcaption>If you remember nothing else about designing educational XR, remember this.  Credit: Lichaw, 2016.</figcaption></figure>
<p> </p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">These phases describe what is happening to the protagonist. In the case of XR, the learner is the star and they should be brought through these phases in an effective design plan. Table 1 compares a storytelling arc with the Pixar story arc, a story arc example of Cinderella, an XR story arc, and an XR narrative plot example. </p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEgxSOF9gbn39Qj1xwvfMionIyF3hUlJfCENY_ftmNl5rYvZMy6Ywjy7ga3S3gmFKOUDmaZGAiHFtoWeXA3Ae7MpeLHwyHIpHrVUEVU1PrXn2lObTT3lEcfg-IYIMtRx1LT-_BoMLcO9ZRTCCAvJJPhig0Ymej6MhpAElU3xdBf3NOmuDbqQYB50PvAKyvM/w640-h480/Narrative%20Plot%20Table(1).png" alt="Examples of the storytelling arc of 6 steps: Literary, Pixar, Cinderella, XR template, and XR example" width="640" height="480" border="0" data-original-height="768" data-original-width="1024" data-is-external-image="true"><figcaption>Examples of the storytelling arc of 6 steps: Literary, Pixar, Cinderella, XR template, and XR example. <br>Pixar story arc from Khan Academy. (2017). <i>Pixar in a box: Introduction to storytelling</i> [Video]. YouTube. <a class="article-editor-content__link article-editor-content__link" href="https://youtu.be/1rMnzNZkIX0" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://youtu.be/1rMnzNZkIX0</a> Cinderella story arc derived from Kurt Vonnegut, as documented by Derek Sivers. (2009, September 1). <a class="article-editor-content__link article-editor-content__link" href="https://sive.rs/drama" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://sive.rs/drama</a></figcaption></figure>
<h3 class="article-editor-content__heading">Example of Narrative Plot in XR</h3>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph"><strong>Introduction.</strong> The who, what, where, why, when of the experience is explained. The scene opens. This starts before the digital experience begins and lasts 30 seconds to a few minutes into the experience, depending on how much needs to be explained. This is the beginning of the exposition.</p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph"><strong>Set the scene. </strong>Provide guidance on the affordances within the experience, how to communicate, walk, navigate, where is help (e.g. where is a digital companion). The learner is invited to move, change appearance, and communicate.</p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph"><strong>Dilemma.</strong> Introduce the conflict or the scenario that the learner will participate in. The learner is presented with a challenge or problem. This is the inciting incident and rising action phases. This can be a great time to guide and practice small solutions to small problems.</p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph"><strong>Crisis.</strong> The learner must act and initiate some sort of change. It is action-oriented, and the learner is on center stage.</p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph"><strong>Change or Denouement.</strong> The results of the change have an impact on consequences or the environment. Said another way, the change ripples through the experience to change it for the learner. The results are non-trivial and not haphazard.</p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph"><strong>Resolution or End.</strong> The mission is complete, and the world has changed around the learner. The learner is living out the consequences of their decision.</p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">Some research has shown that most of the instructional emphasis does not need to be within the XR experience itself. <a class="article-editor-content__link article-editor-content__link" href="https://www.youtube.com/live/l3tw6O8Hn-s?feature=share&amp;t=1663" rel="noopener noreferrer">Dede</a> (2021), when reflecting on what he now believes after over five decades of immersive learning research, said:</p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">“I used to believe that if you had resources, you should spend 95% of the resources on the immersive experience and then you just do a little thinking about what kind of induction you use before people go into immersion and what kind of post experience debriefing you do.  I’ve come to believe now that the induction and debriefing is where the learning takes place predominantly, and so designing those is very important.”</p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">This indicates the importance of the on-boarding and the follow up experiences. The story of an experience begins before something is activated and ends long after.</p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph"><strong>The main point of keeping a narrative plot mindset in ID XR design is to keep the learner at the center of the experience. </strong>Every step of the narrative plot approach focuses on what the protagonist- that is, the learner- experiences: dilemmas, crisis, change, etc. This approach, then, keeps the ID focused on the learner’s experience, not the technology. For example, let’s say a platform can recreate the school environment down to the desks and chairs. An ID might reason, ‘This a great place to hold a class! I can assign classes to virtual rooms and the instructor can use web-sharing boards.’ </p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEjZXncQoR6J1Wug8PH_6xKWKZyZ772q3k-w61ChXyhfwngenGGeu2UOf84fgF22mDaQ60YKCspz5N6SJFxJw39YPoKI7ZTg799qmVTW_CE1bl9bnrfgJbl8B-ztIKbX-wPeo_Ev640ahyphenhyphen0Gw0bTa0Q046FAS2sCALYMk4pP7aC7d1C-nTrmXuYGxjphUxM/w640-h354/virtual%20reality%20classroom.png" alt="Capture of a classroom in virtual reality, complete with desks, chairs, and chalkboard." width="640" height="354" border="0" data-original-height="757" data-original-width="1366" data-is-external-image="true"><figcaption>Don't try this in VR</figcaption></figure>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">That approach puts the technology first and does not consider the learner. It also recreates the problems of regular in-person classrooms and throws in a few more virtual problems as well (i.e., poor internet connections might have avatars distractedly appearing and disappearing). Rather, a learner-centric approach might ask “What is the main experience or emotion that the instructor wants the learners to have in this lesson?” As <a class="article-editor-content__link article-editor-content__link" href="https://www.cambridge.org/highereducation/books/multimedia-learning/FB7E79A165D24D47CEACEB4D2C426ECD#overview" rel="noopener noreferrer">Mayer</a> stated, “How can we adapt multimedia technology to <i>aid </i>human cognition?” (2020, p. 15). This might cause the ID to look at the entire XR event differently and not recommend a virtual classroom. There is more on emotion in design in Section 5.2.</p>
<figure class="article-editor-content__figure-image"><figure class="article-editor-content__figure-image-caption"><img loading="lazy" <figcaption ></figure></figcaption>
<figcaption class="article-editor-content__figure-image-caption">
<div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"><a href="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEhvbmd4Pa8tXVctxz3yU-YbTV1T9SYhrmgiC-7Kv67PNs-pXV4llNMp4Amvbk9zNOsy4Jj5Lme_YE7CYp-fn__PMqFzyAf45FMgTFQsZmglzgFc5PSR3AUA2_WD_DQPIadDPAqbtnjcs_CxAYq9hQKmAP1nVcI-w2TqWM5s9iJ9RZSHEGousEvb_fFdI38/s1200/lord-of-the-rings-timeline.jpg" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img loading="lazy" src="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/697/lord-of-the-rings-timeline.jpg" alt="Lord of the Rings Narrative Plot Diagram. Basical huge spaghetti." width="640" height="336" border="0"> sizes="(max-width: 1920px) 100vw, 1920px" srcset="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/697/responsive/lord-of-the-rings-timeline-xs.jpg 640w ,https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/697/responsive/lord-of-the-rings-timeline-sm.jpg 768w ,https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/697/responsive/lord-of-the-rings-timeline-md.jpg 1024w ,https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/697/responsive/lord-of-the-rings-timeline-lg.jpg 1366w ,https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/697/responsive/lord-of-the-rings-timeline-xl.jpg 1600w ,https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/697/responsive/lord-of-the-rings-timeline-2xl.jpg 1920w"></a></div>
<p> Credit: https://fbvisualisation.blogspot.com/2014/04/narrative-charts-tell-tale.html</p>
</figcaption>
<figcaption class="article-editor-content__figure-image-caption"></figcaption>
</figure>
<h3 class="article-editor-content__heading">2 Visual and Sound Range</h3>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">For the ID, the added visual depth and sound possibilities beyond 2D must be designed. However, more to design means more risk. With XR, the added ability to put information anywhere has more risk of overwhelming the learner than helping the learner. Indeed, D. Clark (2022) agrees that Mayer’s Principles lean towards <strong>less is more</strong>.</p>
<h3 class="article-editor-content__heading">2.1 Visuals</h3>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph"><a class="article-editor-content__link article-editor-content__link" href="https://aperturesciencellc.com/vr/VisualDesignMethodsforVR_MikeAlger.pdf" rel="noopener noreferrer">Alger</a> (2015) noted these basic principles for visual range called the Comfortable Content Zone: 77 degrees of viewing range side to side and a range of 0.5 to 20 meters in depth. There are Periphery Zones to the sides and above, but the learner should be only prompted to use those. </p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEiXlCGMsk_cHdRuq4D9ZKPbgl5DEVXSMv7cehq-y8HfE0xdTrI4nTFh6UZ9SNg4ezMLhusTnsIhuYbZJWTd8uX83DNW85bMlvIrg2MoAab5xZ-AVmROSTnq02oTfoPBjUPYq3yCMwa0ACm2okNvey03RPUSUKc4AUpxgGMf03JOzoqnZ61vKFdbpUmQJXo/w640-h328/Mike%20Alger%202.png" alt="Diagram showing that main content should be placed between 0.5m and 20m to the front of the user. The sides are the peripheral zone and the back/behind is the curiosity zone. Anything within 0.5 of the user is the no-no zone, meaning put nothing there." width="640" height="328" border="0" data-original-height="779" data-original-width="1522" data-is-external-image="true"><figcaption>Credit: Alger, 2015</figcaption></figure>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">This reflects real life. If one was working at a workstation, critical information would be within easy viewing and reach. Other information could be available in what Alger calls the Curiosity Zone – behind and below the learner, but learners should be prompted, as in real life, by sound, light, or foreknowledge, to engage with that non-obvious space (2015).</p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">Alger (2015) further proposes that the visual hierarchy matches the importance of information. To find information in 3D, we look at the center ahead first, then left and right, then below, then above, then finally at our own bodies. Everything above eye level is for things beyond the learner’s control like weather, time, or authority notifications. Everything at or below eye level is within the learner’s control.</p>
<figure class="align-center" ><figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEjgPd-Nq_165ZKbiDQJxV16oX1rcCKGiAhmEMRaqShworqsfFJXlkYwwuTpokKZYL4zun6Qb-s7ChXOEiqID1g-RkuRCGJVxSac_rQ4NaQD2l-I8d6aesK3g3hGVDyjQDv4eYWCfAmb4nFqBkmoTc7v3XcZblx_WacAxH9Hhe9Wrs1kom-nwmQWGHmXC9g/w320-h320/LinkedIn%20Post%20Mike%20Alger(2).gif" alt="Caption describes gif." width="320" height="320" border="0" data-original-height="900" data-original-width="900" data-is-external-image="true"></figure>
<figcaption >Basic visualization of where a VR user <i>would</i> look for something; first center ahead, then left and right, then above and finally at the user's own body.</figcaption>
</figure>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">These user interface principles skew towards conservatism in detail; less is better. IDs should design minimal spaces, with prompts, and within easy arm reach. IDs can create storyboards with isomorphic qualities that both curve around the learner and contain planning space for the foreground, mid-ground, and background visuals.</p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEiIZXzEDc8hv67SXDNmz_lbD6gwTQOJrCPUd0ppq3KU67Dp8VD8gkkKpNfTMHBuylHVeBMtakW7Z88l2Y8nm4xOsFe7pvSRDiZG5mzXO9Ew8LnVzvVxltqXQr3OtYQ4zwcZfMe02lS2NV1p9DpPzHld4zNHJ5WpPzuPVqezcGYvnYLC1CfTSojJPM-UCZg/w320-h288/Mike%20Alger%208.png" alt="Capture showing how designs expand between foreground, midground and background." width="320" height="288" border="0" data-original-height="779" data-original-width="866" data-is-external-image="true"><figcaption>Credit: Alger, 2015.</figcaption></figure>
<p>Credit for below: <a class="article-editor-content__link article-editor-content__link" href="http://ExperienceDynamics.com" rel="noopener noreferrer">ExperienceDynamics.com</a> but I received these XR storyboards from the Interaction Design Foundation.</p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEgxpQ2AIbH43GN1h043L0gql_gJYnbbhVqP1a8f3WHnrtRT8BZ-JEjEYnOtlZwbGu4Ev1uy3zU0juO7kVfoJGXNUe1utg48XkUm6u16Zzc_Mo6bJLhQXI5zq9xizJ_qz9IXYq_4hVtVciMXDe0HkpE0acDFKJluM7Q_FhoMehIYysRoAbg82pNIM3Oe1pk/w320-h219/storyboard%20by%20scene.png" alt="XR Storyboards showing 3 blank scenes" width="320" height="219" border="0" data-original-height="653" data-original-width="953" data-is-external-image="true"><figcaption>XR Storyboards showing 3 blank scenes</figcaption></figure>
<p class="align-left">XR storyboards, blank and capable of showing 3 scenes; the idea might be <strong>one scene per step in narrative plot.</strong></p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEjwknijhw0-22K0xby27LN8DOrQfeu3iMsnfsQJidh36rs_TlndvCK4yQHnB1JymUEzoQS4ACHS47iiASKxeIYr0UXxySvpIOaMarJLLssJ3ksvEOdHFTlcCV1YeHafiG9FHbPx7L70GiaDns_97_etnhvcx4wP1aJEl1_iynSuh2fIhTo_VTostq4RqdM/w320-h184/storyboard%20templates%201.png" alt="A center grid pattern has 4 rectangular grids out in front showing design spaces to use in XR around a user." width="320" height="184" border="0" data-original-height="785" data-original-width="1365" data-is-external-image="true"><figcaption>A center grid pattern has 4 rectangular grids out in front showing design spaces to use in XR around a user.</figcaption></figure>
<p>Another type of XR storyboard; this showing 4 possible areas for the user to look at.</p>
<div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"><a href="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEgAuvlLjoDcAk9_IzqpgRGubagfz6EkH5zzH0uTMa8JoKH1GKxjMZvQ57HrUaMd6A8GzET6aAr3V1zZDkMYoi5lFmdMRUJxkd_v0n9eLWvAODJ5u69sJD9JL46Q_C30N_R0fQfi4xuBPNrLHFgleiOZ7lt3NFvcLdeLp-FJdzNP-EIqMjgIZSVS0TuKjHY/s700/storyboard.png" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;">
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/697/storyboard.png" alt="Single scene XR Storyboard, emphasis on zones around the user." width="320" height="234" border="0" sizes="(max-width: 1920px) 100vw, 1920px" srcset="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/697/responsive/storyboard-xs.png 640w ,https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/697/responsive/storyboard-sm.png 768w ,https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/697/responsive/storyboard-md.png 1024w ,https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/697/responsive/storyboard-lg.png 1366w ,https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/697/responsive/storyboard-xl.png 1600w ,https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/697/responsive/storyboard-2xl.png 1920w"><figcaption>A single XR scene storyboard. Emphasis on the zones around the user.</figcaption></figure>
</a></div>
<h3 class="article-editor-content__heading">2.2 Sound</h3>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">Immersive sound is a rising field within XR design. Poor sound can ruin an XR experience. Experiences can have <strong>spatial sound</strong> where the loudness drops off over virtual distance or <strong>flat sound</strong> where the loudness is the same throughout the entire space. As much as possible, it is good accessible practice that <strong>all senses should have learner controls</strong>: brightness, sound, movement, and intensity. </p>
<p> </p>
<div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"><a href="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEhBqUl49v-gCf22SBsEglRaA7fJ-IpSZ3AjvEVFz1jnz45gxmxxg2JMyHKlQhQZUUh9hTxQSj5CRRXdyWNCk57ZJm8ZqrLMsE1rr0P3lCb0q9wn5GpmcPhJdw5yb8ReStgtkDck0Wpu1kFXOSPpTeWwWskO2HELQdUxBBvalp5uNy0gEt8iNUkUUSSFfBA/s1024/cosmonious-high-vision-accessibility-update-1024x576-1458925651.jpeg" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img loading="lazy" src="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/697/cosmonious-high-vision-accessibility-update-1024x576-1458925651.jpeg" alt="Capture of inside Cosmonius High game showing more accessibility features that users can select." width="320" height="180" border="0" sizes="(max-width: 1920px) 100vw, 1920px" srcset="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/697/responsive/cosmonious-high-vision-accessibility-update-1024x576-1458925651-xs.jpeg 640w ,https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/697/responsive/cosmonious-high-vision-accessibility-update-1024x576-1458925651-sm.jpeg 768w ,https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/697/responsive/cosmonious-high-vision-accessibility-update-1024x576-1458925651-md.jpeg 1024w ,https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/697/responsive/cosmonious-high-vision-accessibility-update-1024x576-1458925651-lg.jpeg 1366w ,https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/697/responsive/cosmonious-high-vision-accessibility-update-1024x576-1458925651-xl.jpeg 1600w ,https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/697/responsive/cosmonious-high-vision-accessibility-update-1024x576-1458925651-2xl.jpeg 1920w"></a></div>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">After Cosmonious High from Owlchemy Labs did some vision updates, they had over 1.53 million times users put their hand over an object to request text-to-speech--in one month and only with Quest users. Still think accessibility features are optional?</p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">Many platforms and experiences already contain volume controls for separate parts of the experience (e.g., voice chat, environment, or notifications all have separate volume controls). Learners should be trained on these controls at on-boarding.</p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEhIoY1ckmx7Kp1Iz98azjJ3-l8KCAtrMSs7ogVLugIKlF1CivfuUx4hUGYtM6ll6UxkrwL9xdflfqtGjOYXNmraN-3RmepvkqrUcSxHR_-HnB1BrOGqDEnepdEkydQBp9ktx8Qm7G5b5PyMl9rTNtxfNKM0L2I3swfaYkhqUqOi1a7Va5fOwlJPsd_OtYg/w320-h270/Cosmonius%20High%20accessibility%20sound%20text.png" alt="Capture from inside Cosmonious High game showing accessibility features" width="320" height="270" border="0" data-original-height="1273" data-original-width="1509" data-is-external-image="true"><figcaption>Cosmonious High capture of some accessibility settings. Note that only one hand is needed to play this VR game.</figcaption></figure>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">Generally, for information that is necessary for the learning event:</p>
<ul class="article-editor-content__bullet-list">
<li class="article-editor-content__list-item">
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">If the information is in speech, provide text equivalents (e.g., transcript).</p>
</li>
<li class="article-editor-content__list-item">
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">If the information is in sound (environmental sounds or notifications), it should have equivalent visual and/or text indicators.</p>
</li>
<li class="article-editor-content__list-item">
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">If the information is in text only, provide sound equivalents.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="article-editor-content__heading">2.3 Interaction &amp; Movement</h3>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">Interactions in XR could be reaching, grabbing, and moving. Good experimental research exists from organizations like <a class="article-editor-content__link article-editor-content__link" href="https://ieeevr.org/" rel="noopener noreferrer">IEEE VR</a> or <a class="article-editor-content__link article-editor-content__link" href="https://iui.acm.org/2024/index.html" rel="noopener noreferrer">ACM IUI</a> on 3D user interface recommendations. Alger’s (2015) design advice showed a seated avatar seated work will be more comfortable than standing in XR.</p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEivAIDkUkL9l7ilOq52s0sm-xU_k16cknx9h7MgKZTjyz2fnvlxoaRJvM9xt7E6En-mRoxMbDltFjf8Rfst-SwDwdMYjBGdxAUfirFe2S51vlv7PA52q14oNKKdgOWd8yIzteqkFfwatiBEff_Y84HOlzzXUNetHzZKrkCXJ3yhvWv6hV_URVhCCmuFINE/w640-h562/Mike%20Alger%205%20zones.png" alt="See Mike Alger's 2015 thesis for more but these images show where a user can be reasonably be asked to reach or gesture." width="640" height="562" border="0" data-original-height="930" data-original-width="1060" data-is-external-image="true"><figcaption>Alger, 2015.</figcaption></figure>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">Almost every new XR user has walked their avatar into a wall. It happens. </p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEhP-w38jE54vtgDNf5mkFrPrh32EnjmGyyInAPf4oD83J0Y1K7nTaQLpBLErGZtE78uA72g-pD1zvrs8arJZXeiPTmeHavuEOH8g2VXwfNpNqeH9-WvUzjW9FkS7M2VTq1fVsMICpKAK7rqqGSU3fmGlvzrfi3wTRO_SWIwo0r6BpooU6zI8Pckc1mHVa8/w400-h308/Peter%20must%20stand%20in%20the%20corner%20after%20the%20Workshop%20meeting.png" alt="Capture of my friend Peter when he walked his avatar into a corner." width="400" height="308" border="0" data-original-height="726" data-original-width="946" data-is-external-image="true"><figcaption>You stay in that corner until you can act like a good avatar, Peter!</figcaption></figure>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">Given that the wall isn’t real, mistakes like this are forgiven quickly. IDs can ask learners to move. </p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">(And Peter knew I took his picture at this moment above.)</p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">Movement in XR is an advantage of the metaverse. While research does not indicate that movement causes learning, it can greatly assist in the storytelling aspect of bringing a learner through an experience by requesting that the avatar move <i>through the story</i> in virtual space time.</p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">Movement is <i>relative</i> in this media. Frame of reference can be manipulated. The avatar can move, or the avatar can stay in one place and the scenes can move or change around them. There are a LOT of <a class="article-editor-content__link article-editor-content__link" href="https://www.tomshardware.com/picturestory/807-virtual-reality-games-locomotion-methods.html" rel="noopener noreferrer">choices for movement in XR</a>. From gaming research, it looks like most of the possibilities are aiming to reduce vestibular mismatch.</p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">In this area, movement-based engagement can be an area of exploration in designs. For example, asking learners to move to one side of the room or another is an interesting way to run a poll. XR movement often includes dancing and flying. Future research should explore the use of controllers or hand detection for learning.</p>
<h3 class="article-editor-content__heading">2.4 Emojis</h3>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">Many social XR platforms have incorporated emojis and they can be used for their apparent reasons: love, happy, sad, clapping, or raised hand. Within designs, learners can use them differently, that is for feedback, poll indicators, or silent ‘I need help’ indicators. Learners have been known to redefine emojis to mean whatever makes sense to them during a learning event.</p>
<p> </p>
<div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"><a href="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEhX6Lklsgk73sRtkPk4Wv6k40DDqkilg2uh1HOUcXF_CbkEkWV7hldIN1NM27U8HMaSTL1mzT7PWD2pocq0UhdoY1k-GPAY8LP0aGCH8OrwMEGJ41cZTcbaBbLkYkFqxzVQadnV-xP_vcy25aWr1VN86dmwFusmMuc9lVQ8GGPPHo5FPsR9auVcpAuR7Bk/s600/relle2020-02-22_12-42-01.jpg" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img loading="lazy" src="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/697/relle2020-02-22_12-42-01.jpg" alt="Capture of a great moment from the start of the International Summit of Educators in VR. Each avatar chose to express a heart/love emoji." width="400" height="286" border="0" sizes="(max-width: 1920px) 100vw, 1920px" srcset="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/697/responsive/relle2020-02-22_12-42-01-xs.jpg 640w ,https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/697/responsive/relle2020-02-22_12-42-01-sm.jpg 768w ,https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/697/responsive/relle2020-02-22_12-42-01-md.jpg 1024w ,https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/697/responsive/relle2020-02-22_12-42-01-lg.jpg 1366w ,https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/697/responsive/relle2020-02-22_12-42-01-xl.jpg 1600w ,https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/697/responsive/relle2020-02-22_12-42-01-2xl.jpg 1920w"></a></div>
<p> Cheers to Educators in VR for their use of emojis during their International Summit in 2020. Part 7 will cover designing and building XR experiences for learning. See you there!</p>
<hr>
<p><br><a name="more"></a> <a class="article-editor-content__link article-editor-content__link" href="https://heatheredodds.blogspot.com/2023/10/instructional-design-in-metaverse-part-1.html" rel="noopener noreferrer">Part 1</a> was the Introduction.</p>
<p><a class="article-editor-content__link article-editor-content__link" href="https://heatheredodds.blogspot.com/2023/10/instructional-design-in-metaverse-part-2.html" rel="noopener noreferrer">Part 2</a> covered Theory and Scope.</p>
<p><a class="article-editor-content__link article-editor-content__link" href="https://heatheredodds.blogspot.com/2023/10/instructional-design-in-metaverse-part.html" rel="noopener noreferrer">Part 3</a> was Myths versus Reality.</p>
<p><a class="article-editor-content__link article-editor-content__link" href="https://heatheredodds.blogspot.com/2023/10/instructional-design-in-metaverse-part_8.html" rel="noopener noreferrer">Part 4</a> covered the Characteristics of Success.<a class="article-editor-content__link article-editor-content__link" href="https://heatheredodds.blogspot.com/2023/10/instructional-design-in-metaverse-part_10.html" rel="noopener noreferrer"></a></p>
<p><a class="article-editor-content__link article-editor-content__link" href="https://heatheredodds.blogspot.com/2023/10/instructional-design-in-metaverse-part_10.html" rel="noopener noreferrer">Part 5</a> was What is the same between 2D and 3D design?</p>
<p>Want to see my full references? <a class="article-editor-content__link article-editor-content__link" href="https://heatheredodds.blogspot.com/2023/10/instructional-design-in-metaverse.html" rel="noopener noreferrer">Have at it</a>.</p>
<p><a href="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEiA_nfjqBD9QWPmQORXVU6vzL9Uh03laNFC9VZYN7Kt_GG7naBYby3NG0-iohzhe-Fq6auRgKlerygpipCB6gOHy2G_7jYIfnz9Ni2EOxkGUx-nA0s4gtEru8LgISLWn4MHCUjv-xa8e0NQKKaGx25plDv_wYX9PBpPN7chRnrhUaQRMKHTsIkik-2MKVw/s1456/heather_dodds_Side_view_in_the_style_of_full_color_charcol_and__a0cf9452-0233-4b7e-98bf-f328dc3cb336.png" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img loading="lazy" src="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/697/heather_dodds_Side_view_in_the_style_of_full_color_charcol_and__a0cf9452-0233-4b7e-98bf-f328dc3cb336.png" alt="Decorative image of our explorer heading out from the library and laboratory now with the glow of knowledge within her." width="640" height="358" border="0" sizes="(max-width: 1920px) 100vw, 1920px" srcset="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/697/responsive/heather_dodds_Side_view_in_the_style_of_full_color_charcol_and__a0cf9452-0233-4b7e-98bf-f328dc3cb336-xs.png 640w ,https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/697/responsive/heather_dodds_Side_view_in_the_style_of_full_color_charcol_and__a0cf9452-0233-4b7e-98bf-f328dc3cb336-sm.png 768w ,https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/697/responsive/heather_dodds_Side_view_in_the_style_of_full_color_charcol_and__a0cf9452-0233-4b7e-98bf-f328dc3cb336-md.png 1024w ,https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/697/responsive/heather_dodds_Side_view_in_the_style_of_full_color_charcol_and__a0cf9452-0233-4b7e-98bf-f328dc3cb336-lg.png 1366w ,https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/697/responsive/heather_dodds_Side_view_in_the_style_of_full_color_charcol_and__a0cf9452-0233-4b7e-98bf-f328dc3cb336-xl.png 1600w ,https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/697/responsive/heather_dodds_Side_view_in_the_style_of_full_color_charcol_and__a0cf9452-0233-4b7e-98bf-f328dc3cb336-2xl.png 1920w"></a></p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">#InstructionalDesign #Metaverse #XR #InstructionalMethod #DirectInstruction #ExperientialLearning #Multimedia #Principles #Mayer #LXD #ID #InstructionalDesigner #WebXR #ImmersiveWeb #Immersion #3D #2D #NarrativePlot #Plot #StoryArc #Storytelling #Pixar #Cinderella #Vonnegut #Introduction #SetTheScene #Dilemma #Crisis #Change #Resolution #LearnerCentric #Protagonist #Visuals #sound #CuriosityZone #ContentZone #PeripheralZone #FlatSound #SpatialSound #teleport #emoji #edtech</p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph"> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Instructional Design in the Metaverse Part 5 Building Blocks</title>
        <author>
            <name>Heather Dodds</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/instructional-design-in-the-metaverse-part-5-building-blocks.html"/>
        <id>https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/instructional-design-in-the-metaverse-part-5-building-blocks.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/698/Part-51.png" medium="image" />
            <category term="Metaverse"/>

        <updated>2023-10-11T14:55:00-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/698/Part-51.png" alt="" />
                    This conceptual series proposes instructional design principles for the metaverse. This is Part 5. Today we start the building blocks of design. And the best news for instructional designers? So much of what we already know from two-dimensional learning will work in three-dimensions. Grab your&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://hobbs-hobbler.github.io/hobbs.blog/media/posts/698/Part-51.png" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">This conceptual series proposes instructional design principles for the metaverse. This is Part 5. Today we start the building blocks of design. And the best news for instructional designers? So much of what we already know from two-dimensional learning <strong><i>will work</i></strong> in three-dimensions. Grab your toolbox, IDs!</p>
<h2 class="article-editor-content__heading">2D to 3D: What Is the Same</h2>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">Technology can benefit learning when the affordances are leveraged towards effective and evidence-based learning principles (<a class="article-editor-content__link article-editor-content__link" href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s10648-020-09592-4" rel="noopener noreferrer">Yeung, Carpenter, &amp; Corral</a>, 2021). Instructional design already has a depth of theory and research that shows that a learning experience is a “systemic, complex design” (<a class="article-editor-content__link article-editor-content__link" href="https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Charles-Reigeluth/publication/371304955_How_Do_We_Solve_a_Problem_Like_Media_and_Methods_207/links/647e04b6b3dfd73b7767f1d2/How-Do-We-Solve-a-Problem-Like-Media-and-Methods-207.pdf" rel="noopener noreferrer">Honebein &amp; Reigeluth</a>, 2023. p. 14).</p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">Yet, instructional designers (IDs) interested in the metaverse in education can be at risk for <strong>two unhelpful mindsets</strong>: first, thinking that <strong>IDs must become developers</strong> or second, succumbing to a ‘<strong>buy first, find a use for it later</strong>’ mentality. The first creates a substantial learning curve with the end result mostly being scenes or environments and 3D objects. Currently, AI is able to create scenes and objects (<a class="article-editor-content__link article-editor-content__link" href="https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Chandan-Kumar-Sahu/publication/348037151_Artificial_intelligence_AI_in_augmented_reality_AR-assisted_manufacturing_applications_a_review/links/5fffd7b545851553a0418910/Artificial-intelligence-AI-in-augmented-reality-AR-assisted-manufacturing-applications-a-review.pdf" rel="noopener noreferrer">Sahu, Young, &amp; Rai</a>, 2021). As a consequence, the need for programmers may decrease. The second mindset leads to IDs to search for educational resources to justify the expense and bother of entering the metaverse. </p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEjeea7qnx2BpCdd1OBqsukeNos2Nv70_t3Lx1BEd5DgsLcKaZF_NAbzZZedXIdCk2eov2t_wX8uVgtbr4MQtXArORUIpfjZKY8jCMnNo_6vzBf-xOmllOase6-DEJBuJkHlcnPyoWvLugDEdkstTatP6biDIFuQuSHXrDxn-G-JbP9BKEvD1LcJPOOPqUw/w640-h142/Buy%20first%201%20blur.png" alt="Capture of a post with text: With the world in such a virtual/hybrid state, I'm curious if any of you have explored using (REDACTED) VR to enhance virtual new hire onboarding experiences. My boss ordered myself and one of my peers our own (REDACTED) devices to explore as this an add on to our current onboarding program, so I'd love to hear from people with similar use cases." width="640" height="142" border="0" data-original-height="543" data-original-width="2444" data-is-external-image="true"><figcaption>Buy first, find a use for it later. Technocentric-design.</figcaption></figure>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">Both of these mindsets <strong>miss the main point</strong> of instructional design. They sacrifice the <strong>learner-centric stance</strong> for a technology-centric stance (<a class="article-editor-content__link article-editor-content__link" href="https://www.cambridge.org/highereducation/books/multimedia-learning/FB7E79A165D24D47CEACEB4D2C426ECD#overview" rel="noopener noreferrer">Mayer</a>, 2020). Many of the 2D-based instructional design models, structures, and principles apply towards 3D learning (<a class="article-editor-content__link article-editor-content__link" href="https://edtechbooks.org/id_highered/immersive_learning_e" rel="noopener noreferrer">Dodds</a>, 2021).</p>
<blockquote class="article-editor-content__blockquote">
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">What we already know should inform us as we make future 3D designs because as <a class="article-editor-content__link article-editor-content__link" href="https://youtu.be/4o__z7aPlMw" rel="noopener noreferrer">Alger</a> stated, “Principles and processes of design are pretty universal because we're usually designing <strong><i>for humans</i></strong><i>”</i> (2020, 3:06).</p>
</blockquote>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">A further extension of this thought would be that IDs are not designing <i>for technology.</i> An ID focusing on 3D design for the first time can have an advantage because their experience will be from a novice’s viewpoint. Learners are novices. Thus, the ID experiences what the learners will later experience for the first time.</p>
<blockquote class="article-editor-content__blockquote">
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph"><strong>Keeping the learner-centric point of view is key.</strong></p>
</blockquote>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">This section emphasizes the use of Mayer’s Principles of Multimedia Design (Mayer, 2020, pp. 400-402, [Reminder, I covered the basics in <a class="article-editor-content__link article-editor-content__link" href="https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/instructional-design-metaverse-part-2-heather-dodds-ph-d-" rel="noopener noreferrer">Part 2</a>]) because they are based on research. This list is not meant as a checklist. This is meant to remind IDs of what the correct design choice <i>would be</i> within a 3D experience.</p>
<h3 class="article-editor-content__heading">1 Reduce extraneous processing</h3>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">The Coherence, Signaling, Redundancy, Spatial Contiguity, and Temporal Contiguity Principles will assist in decisions about types of media (visual, text, audio) and where it will be placed or made available in XR experiences. Because of the enveloping nature of the 3D environment upon the learner, extra unnecessary material could interfere with the learning.</p>
<h3 class="article-editor-content__heading">1.1 Coherence</h3>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">Summary: “Weed out extraneous material”.</p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">ID: Minimize text, sounds, and movement that is not directly related to the learning goal.</p>
<h3 class="article-editor-content__heading">1.2 Signaling</h3>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">Summary: “Highlight important material.”</p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">ID: Use slow pulsating glows, arrows, or narrative prompts to focus the learner on the content.</p>
<h3 class="article-editor-content__heading">1.3 Redundancy</h3>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">Summary: “Do not add printed text that duplicates narration.”</p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">ID: Accessibility concerns dictate that information available via vision or sound should be made available in an alternate form. To follow the spirit of this principle, default settings can be set to include both alternates as activated, which could then be toggled off by the learner at will. XR accessibility research organizations such as <a class="article-editor-content__link article-editor-content__link" href="https://xraccess.org" rel="noopener noreferrer">XR Access</a> or <a class="article-editor-content__link article-editor-content__link" href="https://virtualability.org/" rel="noopener noreferrer">Virtual Ability </a>should be consulted for further guidance.</p>
<h3 class="article-editor-content__heading">1.4 Spatial Contiguity</h3>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">Summary: “Place printed text near to the corresponding part of the graphic.”</p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">ID: There is more space to work with in 3D than 2D. The key with this principle will be to find just the right place to put the text. Some user experience (UX) testing in the form of A/B testing can help find the best placement.</p>
<h3 class="article-editor-content__heading">1.5 Temporal Contiguity</h3>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">Summary: “Present corresponding graphics and narration at the same time.”</p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">ID: Sound and action triggers can be timed within 3D programming.</p>
<h3 class="article-editor-content__heading">2 Managing essential processing</h3>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">The Segmenting, Pre-training, and Modality Principles help the designer place the necessary material in the right place and time for the learner to move the content into sensory memory, short-term memory, and into long-term memory.</p>
<h3 class="article-editor-content__heading">2.1 Segmenting</h3>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">Summary: “Break a lesson into learner-paced parts.”</p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">ID: Plan lessons with storyboards with scenes where the learner moves through the experience. Always provide an escape button that saves learner progress. If that is not possible, a confirmation dialog message can indicate that the learner upon re-entry will be returned to a certain spot.</p>
<h3 class="article-editor-content__heading">2.2 Pre-training</h3>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">Summary: “Provide pre-training in the names and characteristics of the key terms.”</p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">ID: Plan for pre- and post-experience briefing. Pre-training is analogous to reading the box when considering buying a game or reviewing choices in an online store. The learner experience <i>starts</i> there.</p>
<h3 class="article-editor-content__heading">2.3 Modality</h3>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">Summary: “Present words in spoken form.”</p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">ID: Especially for key vocabulary, provide sound files of pronunciation. This especially matters if the experience is designed for solo learner use.</p>
<h3 class="article-editor-content__heading">3 Fostering generative processing</h3>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">The Multimedia, Personalization, Voice, Image, Embodiment, Immersion and Generative Activity Principles help encourage learners to cognitively engage with the material and exert effort to make sense of it. It is this area of design where the ID is making sure that the learners are not passively accepting information <strong>but must do mental work with it</strong>.</p>
<h3 class="article-editor-content__heading">3.1 Multimedia</h3>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">Summary: “Use corresponding words and graphics to explain the material.”</p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">ID: XR is a natural fit for this principle because it nearly always contains simultaneous visuals and sounds. These can be timed together within 3D programming. An interesting design exercise for IDs, however, is to isolate certain aspects of a design and think through how it might work if only one channel of input was working. For example, in a tour of XR spaces, there might be a period of a few seconds of complete darkness between scenes. How are the learners guided by sound only during this time?</p>
<h3 class="article-editor-content__heading">3.2 Personalization</h3>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">Summary: “Put words in conversational language.”</p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">ID: Recorded audio should sound comfortably natural.</p>
<h3 class="article-editor-content__heading">3.3 Voice</h3>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">Summary: “Present spoken words in an appealing human voice.”</p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">ID: This applies most logically in XR to human sources of the spoken words. Poor sound can ruin an XR experience.</p>
<h3 class="article-editor-content__heading">3.4 Image</h3>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">Summary: “Do not put the instructor’s static image on the screen.”</p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">ID: The keyword in this principle is ‘static’. This would rarely be needed in XR. Exceptions might include biographies or eulogies.</p>
<h3 class="article-editor-content__heading">3.5 Embodiment</h3>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">Summary: “Have instructors display human-like gestures, eye contact, facial expressions, and body movements.”</p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">ID: The Proteus Effect shows that users change their behaviors depending on their avatars (<a class="article-editor-content__link article-editor-content__link" href="https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Daniel-Goerlich/publication/347582766_How_Avatars_Influence_User_Behavior_A_Review_on_the_Proteus_Effect_in_Virtual_Environments_and_Video_Games/links/624997f421077329f2eec0f7/How-Avatars-Influence-User-Behavior-A-Review-on-the-Proteus-Effect-in-Virtual-Environments-and-Video-Games.pdf" rel="noopener noreferrer">Praetorius, &amp; Görlich</a>, 2020). Employers are becoming more interested in the use of the metaverse for meetings (<a class="article-editor-content__link article-editor-content__link" href="https://arpost.co/2022/11/11/expressvpn-survey-immersive-tech-workplace/" rel="noopener noreferrer">Jaehnig</a>, 2022). It is reasonable to predict that educators will be holding meetings that are now on-campus or in Zoom with their learners in the metaverse within five years. Due to the demand for these human-like behaviors, avatar creators and platforms are adding more movements like blinking, sitting, or gesturing.</p>
<h3 class="article-editor-content__heading">3.6 Generative Activity</h3>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">Summary: “Add prompts to engage in generative activities such as summarizing, mapping, drawing, imagining, self-testing, self-explaining, teaching, and enacting.”</p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">ID: Interestingly, here the research reaches a nexus; several different sources point in the same direction. Mayer called these generative activities and points to their use <i>within the learning act</i>, as a guided form of practice, “Insert prompts to engage in generative learning activities within the instructional episode” and “learners must use the material from the lesson rather than simply remember it” (2020, p. 371). From this, an activity within XR would be ideal. However, generative activities are not exclusive to happening within XR. Wallace stated in <a class="article-editor-content__link article-editor-content__link" href="https://endurancelearning.com/blog/id-for-non-training-professionals/" rel="noopener noreferrer">Washburn</a> (2023) that all learning points to some place in the future where the results are played out–ideally in a workplace or high stakes setting; it is the final performance that counts. <a class="article-editor-content__link article-editor-content__link" href="https://www.youtube.com/live/l3tw6O8Hn-s?feature=share&amp;t=1663" rel="noopener noreferrer">Dede </a>(2021) pointed out the importance of onboarding and off-boarding as where the learning occurs primarily. Mayer conceded that <strong>generative activities likely need to be taught first as behaviors before asking a learner to perform them</strong> (2020). That is, learners need to be taught what summarizing is before being asked to summarize. This is a valid and somewhat overlooked point. <a class="article-editor-content__link article-editor-content__link" href="https://books.google.com/books?id=PXRJEAAAQBAJ&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;ots=UpbIsA4SJU&amp;dq=learning%20experience%20design%20Clark&amp;lr&amp;pg=PP1#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false" rel="noopener noreferrer">D. Clark</a> referred to these activities as “effortful learning” or “desirable difficulties” (2022, p. 3) and <a class="article-editor-content__link article-editor-content__link" href="https://www.worklearning.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/02/Thalheimer-The-Learning-Transfer-Evaluation-Model-Report-for-LTEM-v11.pdf" rel="noopener noreferrer">Thalheimer</a> (2006) supported retrieval practice, spaced practice, or interleaving approaches. Each of these researchers has a slightly different view into the same problem.</p>
<blockquote class="article-editor-content__blockquote">
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph"><strong>They seem to point to the need for a certain amount of learner effort (not just clicking), with guidance, that should occur <i>within</i> XR and then a follow-on amount of learner effort <i>after</i> leaving XR.</strong></p>
</blockquote>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">What might this look like? Here, we reach the edges of known ID in the metaverse universe [Editor Heather here: fresh off the presses! This just hit ResearchGate last month: <a class="article-editor-content__link article-editor-content__link" href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/374151193_Collaborative_generative_learning_activities_in_immersive_virtual_reality_increase_learning" rel="noopener noreferrer">Collaborative generative learning activities in immersive virtual reality increase learning</a>], but <strong>we can take with us what we already know.</strong></p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">The key question to ask is: <strong>In real life</strong>, where do learners practice in place<strong><i> </i></strong>and later perform when the stakes really matter?  How something is done in real life should be the template that we use to start thinking of how the behavior should be prompted in the metaverse.</p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">Here is an example: Learners do science labs in real life. They practice doing a procedure under the watchful eye of an instructor. It is usually fine if they fail because they can start again but there is some risk and limitation of resources. In XR, the same lab can be set up as practice where learners can repeat interactions, control the speed, and engage in plausible manipulations of scientific equipment (<a class="article-editor-content__link article-editor-content__link" href="https://www.idpublications.org/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/Full-Paper-THE-EFFECT-OF-VIRTUAL-LABORATORY-ON-STUDENT-TEACHERS%E2%80%99-ACHIEVEMENT-IN-INTEGRATED.pdf" rel="noopener noreferrer">Asare, Annan, &amp; Ngman-Wara</a>, 2022). The scripted practice available within XR should be added to other generative activities which could be inside and/or outside of XR such as learners self-explaining what is happening in the experiment during a video recording of the experience or learners teaching what would happen if the variables changed or if there was a chemical spill.</p>
<h3 class="article-editor-content__heading">3.7 Immersion</h3>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">Summary: “Do not convert lessons into 3D immersive virtual reality.”</p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">ID: At this point, this article series would appear to come to a stop.</p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">This last principle basically states do not use 3D. This article series posits, do use 3D, if it is the right thing to do. Returning to the beginning assumptions:</p>
<ol class="article-editor-content__ordered-list">
<li class="article-editor-content__list-item">
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">Learners experience the virtual as real.</p>
</li>
<li class="article-editor-content__list-item">
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">Learning outcomes are expected to be equal to other media.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">It goes to follow, therefore, that if the designs will be accepted by the learners as real experiences and if the learning outcomes are the same as for other forms of media, the decision to go forward with the design should only occur <strong>if the lesson cannot reasonably be done in 2D and meets at least one of the conditions of saving time, money, or danger.</strong> Stepping outside of the learning objective decision, one could argue that 3D allows for added immersion and presence. But in that case, the ID should ask “Is immersion or presence<i> critical to the learning objective</i>?”</p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">Acknowledging the affordance of immersion, Mayer pointed out that the case for immersion is often wrapped into the learner's feelings of interest and motivation (2020, p.361). The logic goes that if a learner is motivated, they will learn more. Research shows that interest and motivation wane and learning performance drains away with it.</p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">The case for presence can be tied with a personal feeling of being there. The more a learner takes on the experience as real and really happening to them, the more the learning should stick with them. Contrarily, research shows that distraction due to extraneous processing seems to cancel any benefit that might be gained (Mayer, 2020). <strong>In sum, the research does not predict at this time that presence will increase learning.</strong></p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">Finally, this tidbit might tip the scales for a decision. <a class="article-editor-content__link article-editor-content__link" href="https://books.google.com/books?id=v1uzCgAAQBAJ&amp;lpg=PR17&amp;ots=TNCJkGdMdm&amp;dq=clark%20mayer&amp;lr&amp;pg=PR17#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false" rel="noopener noreferrer">Clark and Mayer</a> recommended this strategy from e-learning: “Use facilitative techniques that support social presence” (2016, p. 313). This tips the balance of synchronous versus asynchronous learning towards synchronous and shows an affordance <i>not before mentioned:</i> the benefit of social learning in XR.</p>
<blockquote class="article-editor-content__blockquote">
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">Wise uses of XR seem to contain elements <i>of bringing learners together</i>.</p>
</blockquote>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">This should be leaned into in designs, if possible. Therefore, if learning designs can minimize extraneous processing and are best done in 3D, next we should ask what is different about <i>designing</i> for 3D.</p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">That will be Part 6. Stay tuned!</p>
<hr class="article-editor-content__horizontal-rule">
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph"><a class="article-editor-content__link article-editor-content__link" href="https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/instructional-design-metaverse-part-1-heather-dodds-ph-d-/" rel="noopener noreferrer">Part 1</a> was the Introduction.</p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph"><a class="article-editor-content__link article-editor-content__link" href="https://heatheredodds.blogspot.com/2023/10/instructional-design-in-metaverse-part-2.html" rel="noopener noreferrer">Part 2</a> covered Theory and Scope.</p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph"><a class="article-editor-content__link article-editor-content__link" href="https://heatheredodds.blogspot.com/2023/10/instructional-design-in-metaverse-part.html" rel="noopener noreferrer">Part 3</a> was Myths versus Reality.</p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph"><a class="article-editor-content__link article-editor-content__link" href="https://heatheredodds.blogspot.com/2023/10/instructional-design-in-metaverse-part_8.html" rel="noopener noreferrer">Part 4</a> covered the Characteristics of Success.</p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph">Want to see my full references? <a class="article-editor-content__link article-editor-content__link" href="https://heatheredodds.blogspot.com/2023/10/instructional-design-in-metaverse.html" rel="noopener noreferrer">Have at it</a>.</p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEhWJHyMDg5I_QKR9jwka682mXHi6PQ-tOE-4p3mmmPHeCD24lSkRhmS9WBmeB5fs2_tzYNd69qEIj9-oYt1eFp1a2XuRPiSsX-mxdEWYTFIEUIS4X_MZmloYkmaFhbHAj51abQxG2erb5X6wVV09YEZVzuHCZzArobRnryLclE46yfEl6vW8D-RXhDSH3M/w640-h358/heather_dodds_Blend_full_color_charcoal_and_game_cover_of_Legen_b594ba17-d6da-4575-9c4f-477ff847a586%20(1).png" width="640" height="358" border="0" data-original-height="816" data-original-width="1456" data-is-external-image="true"><figcaption>Midjourney and Me. Prompt: Blend full color charcoal and game cover of Legends of Zelda, an attractive woman with short blonde hair and blue eyes wears hooded cloak, casting a glowing spell in a laboratory, cinematic lighting, fantasycore, blue and green color scheme</figcaption></figure>
<hr class="article-editor-content__horizontal-rule">
<p>Originally reposted on October 11, 2023.</p>
<p class="article-editor-content__paragraph"><span id="docs-internal-guid-d457ff87-7fff-a165-a3d4-9641d95e2994" style="background-color: transparent; color: black; font-family: 'Times New Roman',serif; font-size: 11pt; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: 400; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline;">#InstructionalDesign #XR #Multimedia #Principles #Mayer #LXD #ID #L&amp;D #InstructionalDesigner #WebXR #3D #2D #ExtraneousProcessing #Coherence #Signaling #Redundancy #SpatialContiguity #TemporalContiguity #EssentialProcessing #Segmenting #PreTraining #Modality #GenerativeProcessing #Multimedia #Personalization #Voice #Image #Embodiment #GenerativeActivity #Immersion #Presence #EffortfulLearning #DesirableDifficulties #RetrievalPractice #SpacedPractice #Interleaving #LearnerCentric #edtech</span></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
